<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Germane spie truly discovering the deplorable condition of the kingdom and subjects of the French king : being an abstract of the several years observations of a gentleman who made that the peculiar business of his travels : with a continuation of Christianismus Christianandus.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 184 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42665</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G614</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26764</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09533923</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09533923</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43542</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42665)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43542)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1331:34)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Germane spie truly discovering the deplorable condition of the kingdom and subjects of the French king : being an abstract of the several years observations of a gentleman who made that the peculiar business of his travels : with a continuation of Christianismus Christianandus.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Randal Taylor,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A catalogue of French commodities yearly transported into England": p. 71-72.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  Politics and government --  17th century.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIV, 1643-1715.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43542:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43542:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Germane Spie: Truly Diſcovering the DEPLORABLE CONDITION OF THE KINGDOM and SUBJECTS OF THE French King.</p>
            <p>BEING, An ABSTRACT of the ſeveral Years Obſervations of a Gentleman, who made that the Peculiar Buſineſs of his Travels.</p>
            <p>WITH A Continuation of <hi>Chriſtianiſmus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianandus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Randal Taylor,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:43542:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43542:2"/>
            <head>THE Germane Spie: TRULY DISCOVERING The Deplorable Condition of the Kingdom, and Subjects of the <hi>FRENCH</hi> King.</head>
            <p>A Certain <hi>German</hi> Gentleman, a Subject to one of the <hi>Northern</hi> Princes, a Perſon of great Uunderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and no leſs devoted to the good Cauſe; being returned ſome Weeks ago, by the Way of <hi>Italy,</hi> from the Kingdom of <hi>France,</hi> where he Travell'd a long time, and took an extraordinary Care to inform himſelf of all things; with an admirable Exactneſs, has imparted to us in his own Language, a Writing, containing ſeveral Remarks of conſiderable Importance, which he made upon the preſent State of <hi>France;</hi> of which we find it to be our Duty, and for the Intereſt of the Publick Good, that the Nation ſhould be inform'd: To which effect, we immediately with great diligence, ſet our ſelves to Tranſlate the ſame.</p>
            <p>And this we do ſo much the more willingly, becauſe we find that ſeveral Perſons have form'd in themſelves ſuch an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous <hi>Idaea</hi> of the Power of <hi>France,</hi> by reaſon of the taking of <hi>Mons</hi> and <hi>Nyſſa;</hi> that we deem'd it proper to diſabuſe thoſe People, and all others that are led into the ſame Errour.</p>
            <p>Our Author begins with a Diſcourſe of the Beauty of the Country, and Temperature of the Climate, the goodneſs of the Fruits, the agreeable Diſpoſitions and Politeneſs of the Inhabitants, and their Aſſability towards Strangers, which in truth is very great; and after he has entertain'd the Reader for ſome time with theſe things, he tells us,</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:43542:3"/>
            <p>That the Miſeries of thoſe People, are not to be expreſs'd; That there is not any Nation under Heaven ſo oppreſs'd, even in a time of Peace, neither excepting the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> nor the <hi>Turks;</hi> and that thoſe diſtreſſed People are reduced to ſuch a Condition of Poverty, that though the mercileſs Exactors exerciſe in thoſe Places, ten times more Cruelty than an Hoſtile and Victorious Army is wont to do upon a People newly ſubdu'd; nevertheleſs the King is not able to raiſe the half of his ordinary Impoſts, which he rais'd about three Years agoe, becauſe the People have no Money, and for that the Kingdom lies ſo like a Deſart in many Places.</p>
            <p>That this Year there will be a Failure of above Thirty Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, upon the Score of Non-ability to pay.</p>
            <p>That all Manufactures are at a very low Ebb; as thoſe of Silk, Linen, Paper, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And that all the Artificers are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dead, or in the Wars; and that their Trade is abſolutely ruin'd, as well by Land as Sea, as well without as within the Kingdom; and that <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. receives but very little Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney by it: Which is the reaſon, he has been conſtrain'd to have recourſe to violent Means, which are never made uſe of, but when the State is ready to periſh; ſuch as are the Creation of a great number of new Officers, the Borrowing of Thirty Millions, the Augmentation of Officers Fees for large Summs, the extraordinary Taxes upon the Clergy, his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to ſell a great part of his Plate, and the enhauncing the Value of Money; by which means, the King has rais'd above a Hundered Millions, without which he could not have paid his Men this Year.</p>
            <p>That all Proviſions for the Belly, as Corn and Wine, are ſunk above the ſixth part of the Value, which they were formerly worth, and much leſs than what they coſt the Husbandman.</p>
            <p>That they who have Lands to Let, cannot find Farmers, and that the Houſes tumble down, and the Lands lie untill'd.</p>
            <p>That they who have Offices, have no Profit by them.</p>
            <p>That they who have Money due, cannot get the Intereſt of their Money i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a long time, unleſs they be ſuch who have lent Money to the King ſome years agoe, becauſe he thinks thereby to oblige all thoſe that have Money, to lend it him.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:43542:3"/>
            <p>That all the Subjects of that Kingdom in general, are all equally ruin'd: as,</p>
            <p>The Church-men, who formerly were very Wealthy and Powerfull, but now their Lands and other Eſtates no longer yeild 'em any Mony: And for the inferiour Clergy, they have nothing to doe, for they neither Marry, nor Baptize, nor Bury; all the Men being kill'd in the Wars.</p>
            <p>The Grand Nobility live onely upon their Penſions, and Court Employments: The Gentry are a Body the moſt miſerable in the World, and which ought to curſe the Reign of this King.</p>
            <p>The Officers of Juſtice, of the Politick Government, and the Finances receive no Benefit, either by their Eſtates or Emploi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and yet the <hi>King</hi> loads them every day with new <hi>demands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Univerſities, Colleges, and Academies for Riding, Dancing, and Exerciſe of Arms, are all ſo low, that the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters die for Hunger.</p>
            <p>That whereas prudent Princes never make War, but with one Part of the Revenue of their Subjects, and never Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, but to Enrich and People their Dominions, <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. has devour'd in War three Fourths of all the Funds of the Kingdom, and is haſtning to eat up the Remainder; and that his own Subjects are a thouſand times more miſerable, than the People which he has Conquer'd; as appears,</p>
            <p>Firſt, In that the Lands and the Houſes, one with another, are not worth above the fourth Part of the Revenue, of what they were worth; beſides, that there is no Rent to be ſeen, and to fell them, they would not yield a ſixth part.</p>
            <p>That there is a fourth Part of the Houſes, that fall to ruin; and a fourth Part of the Lands, that are thrown up.</p>
            <p>That the Husbandman, who formerly gained 8 Sous a day, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the Country, now gets not above two, and that pay'd him in Corn, of which a Buſhel that was formerly commonly worth 30 <hi>Sous,</hi> is not worth above five or ſix; and withall, that there is very little Corn in the Kingdom, take it in general.</p>
            <p>That by conſequence, the King has devour'd all the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney that was due to the Rich Men of the Kingdom, by the Loans of Money to particular Perſons; and this exceeds above a third Part of all the Stock of the Kingdom. For Lands,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43542:4"/> Houſes, and Rents being eaten up, the Mortgages muſt fail.</p>
            <p>That he has ſeveral times devour'd the Offices and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments of the whole Kingdom, which he ſold at dear Rates, and which were to him inſtead of a Grand Principal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, which produc'd nothing to the Officers.</p>
            <p>That all theſe Offices of Judicature, Civil Policy, and the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, could not have coſt leſs than eight hundred Millions, and that the ſmall Wages which they receive from the King, are ſwallow'd up in the Taxes which they pay from time to time.</p>
            <p>That the innumerable multitude of theſe Offices, and of their exorbitant Prices is ſuch, that theſe People having but ſmall Wages, and ill Paid, cannot drain leſs than a hundred Millions a year<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> from the People, by the litigious Pettifog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, their Cheating and Extortion.</p>
            <p>That the King has diſſipated above two Thirds of the Coi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Money of the Kingdom, as well by exhauſting the Price, as by tranſporting it out of the Kingdom, and beſides that has devour'd two Thirds of the Plate within theſe 40 Years.</p>
            <p>That he has devour'd the Eſtates and Lands of Cities, Corporations, and particular Perſons, by re-uniting them to the Crown Demeaſnes.</p>
            <p>That he has devour'd ſeveral Hundreds of Millions, which he extorted from thoſe that were call'd <hi>Partiſans,</hi> who were Farmers of his Impoſts, whom he deſpoil'd and robb'd, after they had robb'd others.</p>
            <p>That the Kingdom of <hi>France</hi> is diſpeopl'd within theſe Forty years, above half in half; but chiefly within theſe ten Years.</p>
            <p>That there are in the Armies of the King of <hi>France,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween ſix and ſeven Hundred Thouſand Men, including in the Number, a hundred, or a hundred and twenty Toll-ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers, and Subſidy Collectors; and are thus numbred: 50000 Horſe, 18 Dragoons, 33<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>000 Foot, 30000 belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Artillery, and Proviſion, and Ammunition Wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons, and 50000 in his Fleets and Gallies, and above 100 or 120 Camp-Varlets, which make up the number of 700000 Men, the greateſt part of which are Un-marri'd.</p>
            <p>That there are deſtroy'd and die every Year, few leſs than a Third part of theſe Men, according to the Liſts of Recruits,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43542:4"/> which are ſo many Females excluded from Marriage. And that at the end of 10 Years, Marriage being ſo much hinderd, above the half of any numerous Nation will come to be deſtroy'd.</p>
            <p>That the Lives of all the People loſt within 10 Years, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Eſtimate, which is made of Men and Women Slaves in <hi>Algier,</hi> amounts to ſeveral thouſand Millions.</p>
            <p>That from the Example of <hi>Paris,</hi> where this Depopula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is leaſt diſcern'd, the reſt of the Kingdom muſt be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly diſpeopl'd.</p>
            <p>That he is very well inform'd, that there are fewer Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in <hi>Paris</hi> by a Third part, than there were about Twenty years agoe, and that they live in extream Miſery there, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the multitude of Coaches, and the great Court.</p>
            <p>That the Houſes, for the generality, ſtill retain above half the value of their ancient Hire; but that the Rent is ill Paid, and ſeveral of the Houſes ſtand empty; that the Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men die there for hunger.</p>
            <p>That there are hardly any Lacquies, Clerks, Proctors, or young Barbers to be ſeen, as being all conſum'd by the War; and that all the reſt of the Cities and Towns of the Kingdom, are in a worſe Condition.</p>
            <p>That there may be ſtill near Ten Millions of Souls in the Kingdom, and that within the laſt ten Years, the number has leſſen'd between 4 or 5 Millions.</p>
            <p>That by the number of Pariſhes, which are Twenty Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Thouſand, compar'd with the number of Men not Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd, which are in the War, or in the number of Collectors, that there ought to be 22 Men, and one fourth in each Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh one with another.</p>
            <p>That <hi>France</hi> can never recover it ſelf, (though the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſhould be chang'd,) without a long Peace, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſhe abandon her Conqueſts and Uſurpations; by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the Manufactures are carry'd into Foreign Countries, the half of the People deſtroy'd, the Money waſted, the Funds charg'd with more Debts than they are worth; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the vaſt Army of Toll-gatherers and Collectors is not diſmiſs'd; the Sale of Offices and Employments is not ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd; and becauſe all thoſe Officers drain'd, exhauſted,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43542:5"/> and ſamiſh'd, will lie ſucking the People to the very Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, as well as the Court; otherwiſe who can believe, though Trade were once again reſtor'd, that <hi>France</hi> can always raiſe the ſame Summs, which ſhe has done for a long time, unleſs theſe Maxims of Injuſtice and Violence be reſtor'd, with which ſhe is over-whelm'd.</p>
            <p>That the Money is extreamly diminiſh'd in <hi>France:</hi> For that for a long time, the King purchas'd the Alliances and Amities of all Princes, corrupted their Miniſters and other, Counſellors, paid large Penſions to make them declare for <hi>France,</hi> or only remain Neuters; expended upon Spies, both great Ones, and thoſe of leſſer Note, conſiderable Summs; ſent Armies out of the Kingdom into the Service of other Princes; purchaſed Cities and ſtrong Holds, as <hi>Dunkirk</hi> and <hi>Caſal,</hi> the Garriſon of which Place ſtands him in a great deal of Money every Year, as alſo <hi>Pigneroll.</hi> The <hi>Hugue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nots</hi> have carry'd out Thirty Millions. The Horſes ſent for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Year out of <hi>Germany; Switzerland,</hi> and other Places ſince the War, coſt at leaſt Six Millions every Year, each Horſe brought from thence, being Valued at 20 Piſtols a piece; for that there are no Breeds of Horſes in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, by reaſon of the incredible Poverty of the People, that cannot compaſs it to have Stocks before hand.</p>
            <p>That in Gold-lace, Embroidery, Cloth of Gold, Fringes and Gilding, there are waſted in <hi>France</hi> above Ten Millions of Livers in that Metall, and in <hi>England</hi> more; adding withall this Sentence, <hi>Ambitioſa Paupertate perit Gallia. Through ambitious Poverty</hi> France <hi>is ruin'd:</hi> And in this is ſhewn the Blindneſs of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, who complain of the Tranſportation of their Money, and that it is ſcarce, while they themſelves in ten Years, deſtroy as much Silver by this means, as there is Money in the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>That all the Money which <hi>France</hi> raiſes by Contributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, does not exceed for or five Millions of <hi>France,</hi> which is not above the Fortieth or Fiftieth part of her Expence.</p>
            <p>That the Trade which remains behind, is very little.</p>
            <p>That the Profit by Privateers is not conſiderable.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, That the War, beyond Compariſon, does leſs miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43542:5"/> to the Confederates than to <hi>France;</hi> That the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, for the moſt part, gain by this War; That <hi>Germany</hi> in general, draws great Advantages from it, though ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Princes and States ſuffer by it; and that thoſe Advantages advance to a conſiderable Value.</p>
            <p>That the Advantages will far ſurmount the Diſadvantages, which <hi>Holland</hi> receives thereby; and that at length ſhe will gain much more than ſhe does at preſent, and will get a large Intereſt, by the principal Summs ſhe now disburſes. That <hi>Spain</hi> will alſo be a gainer, though ſhe loſes at preſent.</p>
            <p>That the D. of <hi>Savoy</hi> will find his Satisfaction for that he loſes, and will loſe much leſs being United with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates, than if he had clos'd with <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. upon the Conditions which he propos'd; for that then he had been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoi'ld paſt recovery, in regard that <hi>France</hi> never keeps her Word. But that <hi>England</hi> gains more than any of the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates, though many People will not believe it.</p>
            <p>That in time of Peace, ten Thouſand <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as well Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters as Servants, travel into <hi>France,</hi> who ſpend three times as much, as the Revenues of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence reckoned at a 100 <hi>Livers</hi> Sterling a piece, one with another. They get, for the moſt part, above a Million Sterling by the Baubles of <hi>Paris;</hi> and that now they get but little by the Manufactures of Goldlace, Silk, large Hats, <hi>French</hi> Glaſs, Woodden-Combs, Paper, Linen, which are ſettl'd here by the favour of the War; by the Salt, Brandy, Sider and Bere, which is made here; by the ſmall Quantity of <hi>French</hi> Wine which is conſum'd at preſent; by the ſeveral Fruits Dry and Green, and <hi>French</hi> Sweat-Meats, which are little eſteem'd.</p>
            <p>That <hi>England</hi> is, at this day, much more Wealthy than <hi>France;</hi> and that if God had afflicted <hi>England</hi> with ſuch a Government, and a King of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Fourteenth's Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, ſhe might doe much more than <hi>France</hi> does now.</p>
            <p>That therefore all Princes, that are tempted to imitate that King in his Humors, to be a Conqueror and an Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Prince, ought rather to ſwallow Poiſon, and quit the World, than to ſuffer themſelves to be over-rul'd by ſuch Barbarous and Curſed Paſſions.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:43542:6"/>
            <p>That indeed, in ſome meaſure, <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. is to be excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for his Attacking <hi>Mons</hi> and <hi>Nyſſa;</hi> as ſuppoſing him to have a good Correſpondence, both in the one and the other, and that his Deſign was thereby, to re-eſtabliſh or maintain the Reputation of his Great Power, of which he began to be ſomewhat doubtfull; and to prevent his Credit from fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, as well among the Rebels in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as among his own Subjects, and at <hi>Rome,</hi> where there is ſuch Diſputing about the Election of a New Pope; and that he thought this would ſtrike a Terror into the Confederates, eſpecially the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> who he troubles the moſt, and therefore would oblige him to make his Peace apart, and others after, or together with him. He was alſo willing to make the World believe, that the Congreſs at the <hi>Hague,</hi> of which he had Intilligence 8 Months before, did nothing aſtoniſh him. And therefore beleiving it was high time for him to Attempt ſomething, he pickt out <hi>Mons,</hi> before any other in the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> and took all his Meaſures to Crown the Enterprize with Succeſs. And the Reaſons why he pitch'd upon <hi>Mons</hi> were theſe: Becauſe it was a Place the moſt advanc'd toward <hi>France,</hi> and for that the Confederates would ſooner make an Invaſion of his Country on that ſide, than any other way; becauſe it was a Place which fetch'd great Contributions out of <hi>France,</hi> and the Conquer'd Provinces, and for that being large and wealthy, it might ſerve to make a Magazine for K. <hi>William</hi>'s Army; and becauſe that if the Confederates were ſo far weakn'd, as to make a Peace to his Advantage the next Winter, he would rather keep it, than <hi>Aeth, Oudenard,</hi> or <hi>Charleroy,</hi> which he had been once already oblig'd to quit, to ſerve as a Bar to the <hi>Spaniſh Low-Countries;</hi> beſides that, it is the Capital City of a large Province, which the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of that Town would reduce wholly under his Subjection. As for <hi>Nyſſa,</hi> aſſuredly it was Bought and Sold; for that other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it would have been a fooliſh attempt to have Attacqu'd it in the Heart of Winter, being a Place Impregnable; and that the Traitors were agreed, to cover their foul Play, to fire the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, under the Favour of the firſt Bombs that <hi>Catinat</hi> ſhould throw into the Town; by which means they ſhould take the <hi>French</hi> Money, yet appear honeſt Men. That as for the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43542:6"/> and the Soldiers kill'd by the Accident, it might all be ſo manag'd, as if the whole had happen'd fortuitouſly, the better to cover their Intrigues.</p>
            <p>Therefore 'tis preſumed, that <hi>France</hi> went the beſt way to try, whether ſhe could by theſe means ſeparate the Allies one from the other; and farther, that there is no queſtion to be made, but that <hi>France,</hi> by other Intrigues, ſupported with Money, will do her utmoſt to make a Peace the next Winter; for that othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſhe is ruin'd for ever, notwithſtanding all the outward haughtineſs ſhe carries in her looks, and that it is the Intereſt of the Allies, not to be too haſty, but to ſtand reſolutely upon their Terms.</p>
            <p>That whatever outward ſhew <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. makes, it will be impoſſible for him to ſupport another Campaign after this, but that he muſt be oblig'd to conſtrain his Subjects to ſell the laſt remainder of their Plate, and to raiſe the Price of his Money at leaſt half in half. And that all this will hardly ſuffice for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Campaign; for that the farther he goes forward in theſe Exceſſes, and the more his uſual Impoſts decay, the leſs Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney he will have, and the more the People will be ruin'd.</p>
            <p>Having now given you a ſhort, but faithful Account of the Miſeries and Calamities that the <hi>French</hi> King's Subjects groan under at home, as alſo the ſinking Condition of the State; which we may modeſtly affirm to be the Effects of his Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Government on the one hand, and of his Infidelity and Injuſtice towards his Neighbours and Allies on the other; let us now examine the Particulars of his Tranſactions with each Neighbouring Potentate for ſome time paſt, and then let the Impartial judge, whether any thing but Oppreſſion to his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and Ruin to his Kingdom, are likely to be the Events of ſuch perfidious Practices. We will begin with <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How happy was the King of <hi>England,</hi> at his firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration, belov'd by his People, ador'd by his Parliament, and in perfect Union with his Neighbours the <hi>Dutch!</hi> What might not thoſe two Potentates in cloſe Confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy have done? <hi>France</hi> trembled at the thoughts of it, and deſpair'd of graſping Univerſal Empire, unleſs ſhe could
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43542:7"/> divide this ſolid oppoſition, ſo pernicious to her ſoaring Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</p>
            <p>The <hi>French</hi> King well underſtood that the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> would he but put himſelf to the trouble of knowing his own ſtrength, and making a true uſe of it, was in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition not only to mediate, but to force a Peace among all the Potentates of <hi>Europe.</hi> For by a ſtrict Union with the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> he was abſolute. Maſter of the whole <hi>Ocean,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of the Riches of the World; inſomuch that the Mines of <hi>America</hi> were not ſafe to the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> but by his Permiſſion; and by ſending to the weaker ſide the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of his Land Forces, formidable as well for their Courage as their Diſcipline, he was able to have turn'd the ſcales of Victory which way ſoe'er he pleas'd. Now then in regard that by the common Rules of Policy and Fore-ſight, the <hi>French</hi> King could not but be well aſſur'd, that whatſoever Princes he aſſail'd, the other would be as certain in the weakneſs of his Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to have recourſe to the two Grand Fortreſſes of <hi>Europe,</hi> Potent at Sea, and no leſs powerful by Land, to prevent the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vage of his Territories; whether the Dictates of <hi>Achitophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſm,</hi> and <hi>Machiaviliſm,</hi> might not in ſome meaſure juſtifie the moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King, in purſuing the beſt Methods he could to ſeparate ſuch a Conjunction, ſo prejudicial to his aſpiring Ambition and Self-intereſt, may not be ſo much, perhaps, the Queſtion; but whether he is not to be look'd upon as the worſt of the whole Race of <hi>Cain,</hi> and as a Miſchief and Peſt which all Mankind ought to eſchew; who, beſides the moſt unchriſtian like ways, by which he ſought to ſubdue his Enemies, treated his moſt faithfull Friends and Allies with that infidelity, that Treachery, that baſe and ſcornfull Ingratitude, as he did the King of <hi>England.</hi> By which it was plain, that all the Kindneſſes and Remuneration which the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian Lewis</hi> intended the King of <hi>England</hi> for all his Services, was only that he ſhould have been the laſt, that for all his Services and Aſſiſtences given to the <hi>French</hi> Crown, to the over-ſight of his own Intereſt, and his</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:43542:7"/>
            <p>True it is, that notwithſtanding the Convulſions that threatned his Kingdom during his Minority, yet <hi>Mazarine</hi> having by a Conjunction with <hi>Cromwell,</hi> ſurmounted all thoſe difficulties, much increaſed his Power, and inlarged his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts by new Acquiſitions: (For <hi>Cromwell,</hi> whom for his pains <hi>Mazarine</hi> was wont to call a <hi>Fortunate</hi> Fool,) gaping after the Golden Mines of <hi>Peru,</hi> to ſupply his empty Coffers, contrary to all the Rules of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Policy, was altogether for pulling down the diſtant Monarchy of <hi>Spain,</hi> and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing the neighbouring power of <hi>France. Mazarine</hi> had the length of his Foot; and therefore reſolv'd to make the beſt of him, by pampering up his Gold craving humour, and foſtering his Animoſities againſt the <hi>Spaniard.</hi> And ſo cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning was <hi>Mazarine,</hi> that he granted the heedleſs Uſurper what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he demanded, conſidering that when <hi>Cromwell</hi> had aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted him to doe his work, in bringing under the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and by that means caſting the Balance of <hi>Europe</hi> on the <hi>French</hi> ſide, he ſhould afterwards have leiſure enough to recover what he had ſeem'd to part with; which was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards too unhappily verified by the eaſie regaining of <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirk.</hi> Thus <hi>Cromwell</hi> being the firſt that rais'd the <hi>Grandeur</hi> of the <hi>French,</hi> to which he contributed not a little by the War which he made at the time with <hi>Spain;</hi> the two Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that ſucceeded him, were ſo wheedled and bewitched by the <hi>French</hi> Kings ſpecious pretencees and fair Promiſes, that they did, tho undeſignedly too much aſſiſt, him to get up to the Pinicle of Univerſal Dominion; as if this Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King had made uſe of Charms and Philters to faſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinate their Eyes and Ears, neither to ſee themſelves ſo often abus'd, nor to hear the advices of their moſt faithfull Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours.</p>
            <p>How happy was the King of <hi>England,</hi> at his firſt Reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, belov'd by his People, ador'd by his Parliament, and in perfect Union with his Nighbours the <hi>Dutch!</hi> What might not thoſe two Potentates in cloſe Confederacy have done? <hi>France</hi> trembled at the thoughts of it, and deſpair'd of graſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43542:8"/> Univerſal Empire, unleſs ſhe could divide this ſolid op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, ſo pernicious to her ſoaring Projects.</p>
            <p>The <hi>French</hi> King well underſtood that the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> would he but put himſelf to the trouble of knowing his own ſtrength, and making a true uſe of it, was in a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not only to mediate, but to force a Peace among all the Potentates of <hi>Europe.</hi> For by a ſtrict Union with the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> he was abſolute Maſter of the whole <hi>Ocean,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of the Riches of the World; inſomuch that the Mines of <hi>America,</hi> were not ſafe to the King of <hi>Spain</hi> but by his Permiſſion; and by ſending to the weaker ſide the aſſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of his Land Forces, formidable as well for their Courage as their Diſcipline, he was able to have turn'd the ſcales of Victory which way ſoe'er he pleas'd. Now then in regard that by the common Rules of Policy and Fore-ſight, the <hi>French</hi> King could not but be well aſſur'd that whatſoever Princes he aſſail'd, the other would be as certain in the weakneſs of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, to have recourſe to the two Grand Fortreſſes of <hi>Europe,</hi> Potent at Sea, and no leſs powerfull by Land, to prevent the Ravage of his Territories; whether the Dictates of <hi>Achitophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſm,</hi> and <hi>Matchavilliniſm,</hi> might not in ſome meaſure juſtifie the moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King, in purſuing the beſt Methods he could, to ſeparate ſuch a Conjunction, ſo prejudicial to his aſpiring Ambition and Self-intereſt, may not be ſo much, perhaps the Queſtion; but whether he is not to be look'd upon, as the worſt of the whole Race of <hi>Cain,</hi> and as a Miſchief, and Peſt which all Mankind ought to eſchew; who, beſides the moſt unchriſtianlike ways by which he ſought to ſubdue his Enemies, treated his moſt faithfull Friends and Allies with that Infidelity, that Treachery, that baſe and ſcornfull Ingratitude as he did the King of <hi>England.</hi> By which it was plain, that all the Kindneſſes and Remuneration which the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian Lewis</hi> intended the King of <hi>England</hi> for all his Services, was only that he ſhould have been the laſt, that for all his Services and Aſſiſtences given to the <hi>French</hi> Crown, to the over-ſight of his own Intereſt, and his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43542:8"/> Peoples welfare, ſhould have been rewarded with Invaſion and Conqueſt.</p>
            <p>To make this Separation therefore between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> the moſt ſubtile <hi>Mercuries</hi> of <hi>France</hi> were ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad with their Silver Wands, to lull the Britiſh <hi>Argos</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep, and prevent his watching over the <hi>Heſperian</hi> Garden of <hi>European</hi> Liberty; or rather with a deeper Intoxication of <hi>Aurum Potabile</hi> Draughts, to allure his Miniſters into a down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Falſification of their Truſts. Nor was it poſſible for all of them to eſcape, being befaſcinated or to reſiſt thoſe Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Temptations; but, like People that muſt go through with what they have taken money to perform, preſently ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral artificial inſinuations of Injuries receiv'd from the <hi>Dutch,</hi> as to <hi>Amboyna,</hi> and the Fiſhery, were whiſper'd about in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> while at the ſame time the freedom of the Sea, and the preſervation of <hi>Trade,</hi> were with the ſame ſubtilty to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted in <hi>Holland,</hi> on purpoſe to exaſperate the jealouſie of thoſe People. Things that might ſo eaſily have been adjuſted where there had been the leaſt Condeſcentions to Reaſon, that it was undoubtedly above the reach of moſt Mens un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, that the Policy of Great <hi>Britain</hi> ſhould prefer a trivial Quarrel about <hi>Sprats</hi> and <hi>Herrings,</hi> (for the buſineſs of <hi>Amboyna</hi> had been compounded long before,) above the common ſafety of three Nations, and that a Proteſtant Kingdom, without being conſtrained thereto by ſome unavoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable neceſſity, ſhould ever fight with ſo much Rage and Fierceneſs for the Deſtruction of the Proteſtant Intereſt: Or that <hi>Engliſh</hi> Counſellors ſhould adviſe their Prince to run the Fortune of a <hi>French</hi> King, without any rational Proſpect of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to himſelf. But it was plain that the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King was then laying his moſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian</hi> Trains for the Deſtruction of <hi>England;</hi> and as palpable it was, that the <hi>Dutch</hi> War was deſign'd by the <hi>French</hi> to ruine the naval ſtrength of both Nations, and thereby to break the Balance of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope.</hi> It was a Myſtery beyond unfolding, that the Chief Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> ſhould take ſuch ſtrange Meaſures, ſo to miſlead their Sovereign, that in order to the making good
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43542:9"/> his Title to the Kingdom of <hi>France,</hi> he ſhould enable the <hi>French</hi> King to invade all Chriſtendom, and to extend his Empire beyond all bounds; or that to ſecure to himſelf and his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the Sovereignty of the Seas, he ſhould with ſo much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry endeavour to force all the <hi>Dutch</hi> Ships, with all their Naval Power, into the Arms of the <hi>French,</hi> and rejoyce at their Victories as if by Conquering the Land, the <hi>French</hi> did not at the ſame time become Maſters of the Havens, Rivers, and Fleets of the <hi>Dutch.</hi> And yet ſuch was the vaſt Predominan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy which <hi>French</hi> Treaſon, and the hidden Conſpiracies of <hi>French</hi> Counſels had over theſe great Politicians, and the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent which they had over the King of <hi>England,</hi> that he was ſo kind to the <hi>French</hi> King, for ſetting him together by the ears with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> that he ſent him his Vice Admirals, and other Sea Officers, to encourage and promote the ſetting out of his Fleets, and in pity of their want of experience in Sea Affairs, took his raw Seamen by the hand, train'd them up in his own Fleets, among the beſt of his Seamen, and taught them that skill which the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had been many Ages a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; and all this in hopes to enable the <hi>French</hi> King to aſſiſt him in beating his beſt and moſt ſecure friends; wherein the <hi>French,</hi> according to their wonted Treachery, fail'd him too, when they were put to the Tryall.</p>
            <p>All the World would have thought the King ſhould not have ſo ſoon forgot the <hi>Punic</hi> Faith of <hi>France</hi> in their kindneſs to his Perſon, while he was abroad in Exile among them; or if then they might pretend the Intereſt of their Kingdom, and palliate their faithleſs and inhumane Dealing with him by ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Self preſervation; yet no ſuch neceſſity conſtrain'd him to forget the <hi>French</hi> King's oppoſing his Reſtauration with ſo much violence as he did; and his Caballing with his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt enemies to keep him out of his Kingdom, more eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſince he was then ſo ſenſible of it, when it was recent in his Memory; that upon his coming into <hi>England,</hi> he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded away Monſieur <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſadour, and would not ſuffer him to come into his preſence.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:43542:9"/>
            <p>But the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King knew full well how to work himſelf again into the King of <hi>England</hi>'s favour, and at length by throwing a <hi>French Dalilah</hi> into his embraces, quite cut off the Locks of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Sampſon. All on a ſudden <hi>France</hi> ſeem'd to be remov'd into <hi>England;</hi> nothing but <hi>French</hi> Bau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and Gugaws pleaſed our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentry: A <hi>French</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction prevailing at Court, <hi>French</hi> Mountebanks for Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>French</hi> Faſhions, <hi>French</hi> Hats, <hi>French</hi> Lackeys, <hi>French</hi> Fidlers, <hi>French</hi> Dancing-Maſters, <hi>French</hi> Tooth-Drawers, <hi>French</hi> Barbers, <hi>French</hi> Air in our very looks, <hi>French</hi> Legs, <hi>French</hi> Compliments, <hi>French</hi> Grimaces, and <hi>French</hi> Debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, to fit us for <hi>French</hi> Slavery: And had the <hi>French</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe been then unknown in <hi>England,</hi> 'tis to be queſtioned whither it would not have been entertained with as general a Conſent as the <hi>Sichemites</hi> ſubmitted to the Pain of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, though to the hazard of being all deſtroy'd by the <hi>French Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> while ſore and driveling under the Diſtemper. Nor is it to be doubted but the <hi>French</hi> Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity would have as eaſily made tryall of ſuch a Deſign as they did of the reſt of their Tricks, had they thought it would have taken effect.</p>
            <p>It is well known, that before the firſt <hi>Dutch</hi> War was entred into, the King of <hi>England</hi> ſought to make Alliances with <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> but the <hi>Spaniards</hi> were ſo Cock-ſure of the <hi>French</hi> Promiſes, that they would not make any Approaches to Friendſhip with <hi>England,</hi> without the giving up of <hi>Dunkirk, Tangier,</hi> and <hi>Jamaica.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the <hi>French,</hi> a Project of a Treaty was offer'd them, and promoted with all earneſtneſs by the Lord <hi>H—s</hi> at <hi>Paris,</hi> but it was plainly diſcern'd that the principal deſigns of the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King was only to draw the King of <hi>England</hi> into ſuch an Alliance, as might advance his deſign upon <hi>Spain;</hi> and therefore ſo ſoon as he had ſet the <hi>Dutch</hi> and us together by the Ears, and ſaw that thereby the Balance of <hi>Europe</hi> was broken, he no longer minded Alliance with <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland:</hi> But after many Propoſals of Leagues, and many Arts uſed to highten the jealouſies between Us and the <hi>Hollanders,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:43542:10"/> he at laſt ſided with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> though to ſo little purpoſe, that his Intentions plainly appeared to be no other, than to ſee the two moſt Potent Obſtacles of his Ambition deſtroy one another, to the end he might with leſs Oppoſition invade his Nighbours, and increaſe his own Naval Strength. Nay, the Juggle went much farther, for that in the heat of all the War, he ſtill kept Negotiations on Foot, and made overtures and propoſals of Peace, by means of the Queen-Mother, whom in the end he ſo far, and ſo treacherouſly deluded, as to aſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain her, and by her means to aſſure the King of <hi>England</hi> her Son, that the <hi>Dutch</hi> would not ſet out any Fleet the enſuing Summer, and yet underhand preſs'd the <hi>Dutch</hi> with all the Vigor and Importunity imaginable to fit out their Men of War again, with a promiſe, rather than fail, that he would joyn his Fleet with theirs againſt the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Now it was upon a Suppoſal that the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King was at that time a good Chriſtian and true to his Word, in purſuing his pretended Propoſals of Peace; and upon that faithleſs <hi>French</hi> Paroll it was, that the King of <hi>England</hi> put forth no Fleet to Sea that Year, upon which followed that Fatal ſurprize of our Ships at <hi>Chatham;</hi> then which a greater Diſ-honour never hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to the Nation ſince the memory of Hiſtory. But at laſt, as we had been oblig'd to the Craft and Treachery for the War and the Shame we received by it, ſo we were glad to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Peace that enſued from his favour; which was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded at <hi>Breda</hi> between <hi>England, France,</hi> and <hi>Holland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this Treaty of <hi>Breda,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> were oblig'd to reſtore St. <hi>Christophers</hi> to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in the ſame manner and form as is expreſt in the Articles; but inſtead of performing their Engagement according to the true intent and literal meaning of the Articles, they from time to time upon ſeveral unjuſt and frivolous Pretences, deluded and delay'd the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners that were ſent to take Poſſeſſion of it; till finding there was a neceſſity to comply with us in ſo ſmall a matter, while we were preparing to venture a ſecond quarrel in their behalf, it was at laſt ſurrendred, after four year's baffling, to Sir <hi>Charles Wheeler.</hi> However to ſhew the perfidiouſneſs
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43542:10"/> of <hi>French</hi> dealing, before they deliver'd it they deſtroyed all the Plantations, laid the whole Iſland waſte, and left it in a much worſe condition than if it had never been planted. And as if the ſeizure and detaining of the King of <hi>England</hi>'s Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories had not been ſufficient, they interrupted alſo the Trade of his Subjects in thoſe Parts, and aſſuming to themſelves the Sovereignty of thoſe Seas, would not ſuffer any Ships but their own, to ſail either by or about thoſe Iſlands; but as if it had been Criminal ſo to doe, took and confiſcated ſeveral Veſſels up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that account. From all which a Queſtion will ariſe eaſie to be reſolv'd, whither any thing be recorded of the old <hi>Carthaginians</hi> more perfidious than this; and whether the King of <hi>England</hi> might not have expected more Honeſt and Chriſtian dealing from the <hi>unbelieving Turk,</hi> than from the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true, that after the Peace of <hi>Breda,</hi> the King of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> was at lieſure to conſider how the <hi>French</hi> King had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus'd him, by engaging him in a War with his Proteſtant Nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and how he had ſeemingly taken their parts to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the War; that while they were battering, and bruiſing, and weakning one another, he might have the fairer Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, in violation of all the moſt ſolemn and ſacred Oaths and Treaties, to invade the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Netherlands; and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving with what a rapid Torrent of Victory he bore down all before him, thought fit to interpoſe before the flame that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed his next Nighbour, ſhould throw it's ſparks over the Water; and therefore ſent into <hi>Holland</hi> to invite them to a nearer Alliance, and to enter into ſuch farther Counſels as were moſt proper to ſtop the Fury of the <hi>French</hi> King; which offer being by the <hi>Dutch</hi> embraced with open Arms, a defenſive League was concluded in five days time between <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with another for the repreſſing the farther Progreſs of the <hi>French</hi> Armes in the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Netherlands: In which the <hi>Sweeds</hi> afterwards making a third Party concern'd, gave it the name of the Triple League.</p>
            <p>This was no way pleaſing to the <hi>French</hi> King, however for a while he diſſembled his reſentment of the Affront, though from the firſt moment he reſolved to make uſe of all his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43542:11"/> Charms, and Golden Magick to diſſolve this Triple Knot, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it coſt him.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe the Ducheſs of <hi>Orleance,</hi> is ſaid by the <hi>French</hi> to be ſent over hither, believing no Inſtrument ſo proper as the King of <hi>England</hi>'s own Siſter to prevail with her Brother. King <hi>Charles</hi> met her at <hi>Dover,</hi> where their endearments one to another were ſo much the more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocally prevailing, by how much it happens that Princes more rarely than private Perſons enjoy their Relations: And when they doe, yet their kind Interviews are many times at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with ſome fatal diſaſter; of which though there was no appearance here in <hi>England,</hi> yet the firſt News we heard of her upon her Return to <hi>France,</hi> was, that ſhe was dead: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Affair was ſo dextrouſly managed, that a <hi>French</hi> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour was forthwith diſpatch'd out of <hi>France,</hi> and an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ambaſſadour ſent to <hi>Paris,</hi> and as the <hi>French</hi> gave out, a private League was clapt up, to the ruine of the Triple Alliance, to all the highth of Intimacy and Dearneſs; as if upon diſſecting the Princeſs, there had ſome State <hi>Philter</hi> been found in her Bowels, or that a Reconciliation with <hi>France</hi> could not have been celebrated with a leſs Sacrifice than that of the Bloud-Royal of <hi>England.</hi> This ſuppoſed Treaty was a work of Darkneſs, not to be div'd into in a great while, but afterwards the <hi>French</hi> King caus'd it to be made publick, as we ſhall ſee by and by.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, the Knowledg of this was of great Importance to <hi>England;</hi> but the diſcovery was the moſt apparent De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration in the World of <hi>French</hi> Perfidiouſneſs, ſo enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous as it could not be imagined to have entred into the Breaſt of a Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King, ſo treacherouſly to expoſe the Secrets of his deareſt Confederate, after he had drawn him in by all the Aſſurances of his aſſiſtance imaginable: And the reaſons that induc'd him to make the detection were no leſs Impious, though agreeable to the Practice of the <hi>French</hi> King; who after he has made it his buſineſs to decoy in Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that lend an eaſie ear to his Enchantments, or with too much facility ſuffer themſelves to be overcome by his Allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Engagements, into any unſeemly and diſhonourable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43542:11"/> believes he has them then ſafely tack'd to his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, and that they will not dare to flinch from his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, for fear of being expoſed to their People, which he takes care in due time to have artificially inſtill'd into their Ears; a Maxim of Chriſtianity which lies conceal'd from all other Men, but the moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> of Princes: And thus it was, that the <hi>French</hi> King having amus'd the Emperor with the Noiſe of a Treaty, and at the ſame time brought the <hi>Turk</hi> into <hi>Hungary,</hi> to joyn the Malecontents, to excite his Private Confederate the King of <hi>England</hi> to follow his ſteps in Government Bare-faced, cauſes a little Book to be Printed and Publiſhed, with the Privilege <hi>Du Roy,</hi> Entitl'd, The <hi>Hiſtory of the Tranſactions of this Age,</hi> and therein ordered the <hi>Dover Treaty</hi> (as they call'd it) to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, and to that purpoſe furniſh'd his <hi>Hiſtoriographer</hi> with Notes and Directions by the Hands of his Secretary <hi>Colbert,</hi> to the end that the King of <hi>England,</hi> being truly as he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd, ſet out in his Colours, and deſpairing of being ever after truſted by his People, might be enforced to take ſuch Reſolutions as <hi>Deſpair</hi> and <hi>Fury</hi> ſhould inſpire him withall, to the Deſtruction of thoſe he had ſo highly diſoblig'd; there being nothing more than the Subverſion of <hi>England</hi> which the <hi>French</hi> King aim'd at. 'Tis true, he was ſo kind as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call the <hi>Book,</hi> upon the loud complaint of the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>'s Ambaſſador; however it was an apparent Demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to all the World, how little truſt or reliance there was in <hi>French</hi> Amity, and plainly ſhews that there is no way to bind this mighty <hi>Sampſon</hi> by Oath, Promiſes, Treaties, or by any other the moſt Religious Ties and Conſiderations, which are no more to him than Spiders Webs, but by an abſolute clipping off the Locks of his Power, and diſabling him ſo as never to riſe more.</p>
            <p>But to return to the <hi>Triple League:</hi> In the end the <hi>French</hi> King by his wicked Policy ſo contrived the matter, as to cauſe a new Rupture twixt the <hi>Dutch</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> and as if he had intended to be the Maſter of Iniquity, and to make the King of <hi>England</hi> as bad as himſelf nothing would
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43542:12"/> ſuffice till he had prevail'd with the King to attack the <hi>Dutch Smyrna</hi> Fleet returning home, and dreaming of no ſuch matter; which, as it was contrary to the <hi>Genius</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, and to the Nature and Gentle Diſpoſition of the King of <hi>England</hi> himſelf, is wholly to be attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the Wiles and wicked Temptations of the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Prince, who never ceas'd pealing it into the King of <hi>England</hi>'s Ears, that if he could but maſter the Wealth of the <hi>Smyrna</hi> Fleet, he ſhould never want Mony again. And being thus betrayed by wheedling <hi>French</hi> Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucination, what can the <hi>French</hi> expect but the Severity of <hi>England</hi>'s juſt Revenge; wherein we may venture with the greater hopes of Succeſs, as being engaged with all in the common Cauſe of Chriſtendoms Tranquillity.</p>
            <p>Add to this, that when the <hi>French</hi> King thought the King of <hi>England</hi> was engaged ſo far by the <hi>Smyrna Attack,</hi> as that he muſt needs go forward, the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King then open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declared, 'twas none of his Quarrel, and that he only en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in it to aſſiſt the King of <hi>England,</hi> merely in reſpect to His Perſon: By which means the King of <hi>England</hi> was again betrayed and neceſſitated to declare War firſt, and to expect the Aſſiſtance of his Confederate afterwards.</p>
            <p>Nor is it leſs obſervable, that the <hi>French</hi> King, in conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with a Proteſtant Prince, to render him odious among all the States and Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> whether Proteſtant or Roman Catholick, gave it out, that the War againſt the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Provinces was a War of Religion, undertaken merely for the Propagation of the Roman Catholick Faith, and as the <hi>French</hi> Miniſter expreſſed it in a Solemn Speech to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror's Council, that the <hi>Hollanders</hi> being Hereticks, who had forſaken God, all good Chriſtians were bound to Unite to their Extirpation. To confirm which the more, the <hi>French</hi> Miniſters, no doubt not contrary to their Inſtructions, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd and aſſur'd many Princes, that to let all the World ſee how far their Maſter was from any ſuch Ambitious deſigns as were laid to his charge, and to ſatisfie the World that he entred into the War merely out of a Religious Zeal, and for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43542:12"/> the Glory of God; he was ready to part with all his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, and to reſtore to the <hi>Hollanders</hi> all the Towns he had won from them, if they would but re-eſtabliſh the True Worſhip they had baniſh'd out of their Dominions. Such is the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King, who ſcruples not to falſifie with Heaven, ſo it may but ſupport and colour his falſhood upon Earth.</p>
            <p>Well, the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King, having by his Ungodly Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy thus engaged us in a Bloudy War with <hi>Holland,</hi> purſues his own deſign by Land with all the Vigour Imaginable, in ſo much, that the ſwiftneſs and force of his Motion ſeem'd to be ſomewhat Supernatural; but all this while he leaves us to doe our own work by Sea. 'Tis true, his Fleet appeared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, and made up a third Squadron under white Colours, but under that Colour of Innocence, they thought it ſuch a crime to ſhed Bloud, that they always kept out of harms way: Rather they did us more miſchief than good, in regard that when our Admirals encountr'd the Enemy in hopes of their Aſſiſtance, they always left the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in the Lurch to bear the Brunt of the Engagement againſt the ſuperiour Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, which it was their Duty to have attack'd. A peice of Treachery ſo inſupportable, that only they who ſuffer'd it would have endur'd it, by which the whole <hi>Engliſh</hi> Navy was abſolutely betrayed by a faithleſs Allie, and by which the Lives of great numbers of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were loſt, which by their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction might have been ſav'd. So that it was apparent that thoſe ſacred Ships of the <hi>French</hi> were a ſort of <hi>Noli me Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere's,</hi> not ſent to aſſiſt their Confederares, but only to ſound the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Seas, to ſpy our Ports, to learn our Building, to contemplate our way of Fighting, to conſume ours, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their own Navy, to encreaſe their Commerce, and to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all ſo, that the two great Naval Powers of <hi>Europe</hi> having cruſh'd one another, he might remain ſole Lord of the Oce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and by conſequence Maſter of all the Trade of the World,</p>
            <p>Thus it happen'd, that after three Engagements of Ours againſt the <hi>Dutch Fleet</hi> in one Summer, while nothing was
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43542:13"/> tenable at Land againſt the <hi>French,</hi> it ſeem'd that as to us every thing at Sea was Impregnable; which was not to be attributed either to want of Courage or Conduct, but was only to be imputed to our unfortunate Conjunction with the perfidious <hi>French</hi> like the misfortunes that happen to Men by being in ill Company.</p>
            <p>This Misbehaviour of the <hi>French</hi> rais'd the Indignation of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to ſuch a Pitch, that the Parliament reſolving to give no more Mony for the continuance of the War; the King was perſuaded to make a Peace with <hi>Holland;</hi> which was concluded accordingly, towards the latter end of the Year 1673.</p>
            <p>And to ſhew that the King of <hi>England</hi> had all the reaſon in the World ſo to doe, we are to take a little farther proſpect of the uprightneſs of the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King to his Friend and Allie, who had at ſuch a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t expence of Treaſure eſpous'd his Quarrel.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>French</hi> Army having paſſed the <hi>Wale,</hi> caus'd ſuch a General Conſternation all over <hi>Holland</hi> and the Confuſion they were in was ſuch, they could hardly reſolve whether to yield or continue to defend themſelves. The States there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſent away ſeveral of their Deputies, ſome to the King of <hi>England,</hi> others to the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> of Princes, to know of both upon what conditions they would be willing to make Peace and Agreement.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that were ſent to the King of <hi>England</hi> (to ſhew how juſtly he intended to have dealt with the <hi>French</hi> or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were out of Fear of giving him any Jealouſie or Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,) were met as far as <hi>Graveſend;</hi> and being forbid their approach to <hi>White-Hall,</hi> were conveigh'd to <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> and there, as it were, honourably confin'd, till his Majeſty of <hi>England</hi> could hear from the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King, whether thoſe Deputies might be admitted.</p>
            <p>But the other Deputies no ſooner arriv'd at the <hi>French Court,</hi> but two Secretaries of State were ſent to them, who, without farther delay, demanded in the firſt place what Power they had to Treat; and next, what Propoſals they had to make in order to a ſpeedy Peace.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:43542:13"/>
            <p>The Deputies anſwered, they came not to make Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals, but to receive Conditions from his Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, as it better became them. Upon which, to haſten them to a Concluſion, the <hi>French Miniſters</hi> told them in ſhort, That whatever his Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Majeſty had conquer'd, in their Dominions, he lookt upon as his own already and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore would not part with it, without an Equivalent, as well for what he might farther ſubdue, before the concluſion of the Treaty, as for what he had already in Poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>With this Anſwer Monſieur <hi>De Groet,</hi> one of the <hi>Holland</hi> Deputies, poſted back to the <hi>Hague,</hi> and with no leſs ſpeed was ſent back again with full Inſtructions and Authority, jointly with the reſt of his Colleagues, to treat and conclude a Peace with them.</p>
            <p>No ſooner was he return'd, but Monſieur <hi>Louvoy,</hi> one of the <hi>French</hi> King's Secretaries, gave the Deputies a Draught of a Treaty, or rather the Pretenſions of the King his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; upon the granting of which, he was both willing and ready to return to his former Amity with the States, and to conclude a firm Peace with them.</p>
            <p>Upon which two things are Obſervable Firſt, that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions themſelves were ſuch, which, if granted would have made the <hi>French</hi> King as perfectly Maſter of the Country, as if he had Conquer'd it by the Sword. And in the Second place, That in all the Articles there was not the leaſt word relating to <hi>England,</hi> nor any more notice taken of the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> than if he had not been at all concern'd in the War.</p>
            <p>And farther, to demonſtrate that it was never the deſign of the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Prince that the King of <hi>England</hi> ſhould be a gainer by the War, Monſieur <hi>De Groet</hi> declared at his ſecond return to the <hi>Hague,</hi> when he carryed the King's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject along with him, that when the <hi>French</hi> Miniſters were ask'd what was to be done with <hi>England,</hi> they made Anſwer, that the States might doe as they pleas'd with <hi>England,</hi> and come off as cheap as they could, for that the <hi>French</hi> were not bound by their Treaty to procure them any Advantages. A great Happineſs in the mean time for the King of <hi>England</hi> to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43542:14"/> be engaged in ſuch a War, with ſuch a Falſe and Treacherous Allie; for it is plain, that the <hi>Dutch</hi> had no ſooner ſignifi'd their deſires, but the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Prince had it preſently in his Head to have cheated the King of <hi>England.</hi> For could the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King in that ſame dreadful Conſternation of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> have got the Poſſeſſion of the United Provinces by the more conciſe, and leſs expenſive way of Treaty, he would ſoon have found an expedient to have defrauded his dear Confederate of any ſhare in them. Which was the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Sophiſter ſpurr'd on the conſternated <hi>Dutch</hi> with ſo much haſte, and with ſuch a clandeſtine ſpeed purſu'd his Advantage, that the King of <hi>England</hi> might not have a Moment's time to provide for himſelf.</p>
            <p>But the King of <hi>England</hi> having ſerv'd the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Prince more juſtly in his kind, by a ſeparate Peace with <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the ſudden Advancement of His Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> attended by the Fall of the <hi>De-witts,</hi> quaſh'd all the lofty <hi>Frenchman's</hi> hopes of gaining, either by Treaty or by Conqueſts, what his thoughts aſpir'd to. So that now, as if he had been arriv'd at the <hi>Tropick</hi> of his Fortune, he was forc'd to roll back again with the ſame ſwiftneſs as he aſcended to the highth of his ſucceſs. However that he might not loſe his old wont, as a mark of his diſpleaſure, and as it were to puniſh the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation for his diſappointments, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Peace that was ſtill firm between the two Crowns, he let looſe his Privateers among the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants, to that degree of <hi>Treaty-Violation,</hi> that from that time for near two years together (Peace all the while, if <hi>French Peace</hi> may be call'd <hi>Peace,</hi>) there was no ſecurity of Commerce or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation, but at Sea they Murther'd, Plunder'd, made Prize, and Confiſcated all they met with. The <hi>French</hi> Pickaroons lay before the Mouths of our Harbors, hover'd all along our Coaſts, took our Ships in the very Ports, ſo that we were in a manner Blockt up by Water. And if any made Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at the Sovereign-Port of the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian Solyman</hi> for Juſtice, they were moſt inſolently baffled, except ſome few who by Sir <hi>E. L</hi>'s intereſt were redeem'd upon ſomewhat
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:43542:14"/> eaſier Compoſition. For evidence of which the following Papers, return'd by certain Members of the Privy Council, in Purſuance of the King's Order, as alſo the Regiſter which was annex'd to it, of the ſeveral Veſſels that were then complain'd of to be taken, are a Memorial not eaſie to be cancell'd.</p>
            <p>So loud and ſo thick were the daily complaints of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants, of their loſſes ſuſtain'd by the <hi>French</hi> Pri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vateers, in the Year 1674. and 1676. notwithſtanding the Publick Amity between the two Nations, that the King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd the Examination thereof to ſeveral Lords of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Trade, who, upon due Examination of the Affair, obſerv'd that the Petition of the Merchants, preſented to the King the <hi>31ſt.</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> 1676. was grounded upon theſe Heads.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That their Ships and Goods, though mann'd accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Act of Navigation, and furniſh'd with all neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Paſſes, were daily ſeiz'd, carry'd into <hi>Dunkirk, Calais, Sherbrook,</hi> and other Ports, the Maſters and Owners kept cloſe Priſoners, to force them by hardſhip to abuſe their Owners, or elſe for the relief of their own private Neceſſities (being commonly Stripp'd and Plunder'd) to enter into the Privateers Service, which great numbers had done with very pernicious Effects.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That the delay and charge of proſecuting the Law in <hi>France,</hi> did commonly make the Owners become loſers of half the Value, when ever they were ſucceſsfull.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That there was no reparation ever gotten from Privateers for what they Plunder'd and Imbezl'd, which made them freely ſeize upon all they met, and perpetually moleſt the Navigation of the King's Subjects; for which Reaſons they humbly implor'd His Majeſty's Relief and Protection.</p>
            <p>Thereupon the King was pleas'd to command that ſome of his Frigats ſhould ſail forth to clear the Coaſt of thoſe Privateers, ſeize them, and bring ſuch as had offended to make Reſtitution. Moreover the King order'd, that the Lords of the Committee of Trade ſhould take good notice of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Caſes and Complaints depending, that ſuch as were
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43542:15"/> of weight and merit, might be fitted for his Gracious Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation for Relief: As alſo to ſurvey the whole number of Seizures which had been made upon his Subjects, in order to lay before his Majeſty what hardſhips had been ſuſtain'd at Sea, and what ſort of Juſtice had been adminiſter'd in <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Obedience to which command, they brought in a Liſt of ſuch Ships as had been ſeiz'd to the number of fifty three; and the Caſes wherein the Owners had repair'd to the King for relief. Which, as in the General it ſuppos'd a Juſtice in ſuch complaints, ſo it left a ſuſpition of great hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips in the Methods of Redreſs; beſides that the number of Captives was no ſmall proof of the facility of Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>While the Lords were in the midſt of this Examination, there was preſented to the Committee, as it was receiv'd from Monſieur <hi>Courtin,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſador, an Extract of a Letter from Monſieur <hi>Colbert</hi> to Monſieur <hi>Pompone,</hi> one of the <hi>French</hi> King's Secretaries, dated <hi>June 28th.</hi> 1676. in theſe Words.</p>
            <q>
               <p>FOr what concerns the Prizes, it would be a difficult mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to anſwer all the Caſes contain'd in Monſieur <hi>Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin</hi>'s Letter.</p>
               <p>What I can ſay to it, is, That the Council for Marine Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs ſits every day at St. <hi>Germaines.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That all Privateers and Reclaimers know it.</p>
               <p>That Sir <hi>Ellis Leighton,</hi> nominated by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador, hath always notice of it, and is always preſent at it.</p>
               <p>That not a week paſſes, but I give him two or three Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diences, and oftentimes I ſend for him on purpoſe.</p>
               <p>That his Reaſons are all read, reported and committed; as likewiſe are all Petitions of Reclaimers, and I ſhall tell you more, I acquaint him with the Reaſons upon which Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is given.</p>
               <p>In giving Judgment, all Veſſels which have any Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of being <hi>Engliſh</hi> are releas'd, and very often; and almoſt always; though we are ſatisfied that the Ships are <hi>Dutch,</hi> yet they are releas'd becauſe there is ſome appearance of their
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:43542:15"/> being <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and every thing is judg'd favourable for that Nation. And it is no leſs true that all Ships that are taken are <hi>Dutch</hi> Built, that they never were in <hi>England,</hi> that the Maſters and all the Equipage are <hi>Dutch,</hi> that the Cockets are for Perſons unknown, and which are not oft-times ſo much as nam'd; that they carry with them only ſome Sea Breifs from <hi>Waterford</hi> or ſome other Town of <hi>Ireland;</hi> that the whole Ships Company depoſes, they were ſent to <hi>Holland;</hi> that we have found on Board three or four Veſſels, Bills of Accompt, by which it is ſeen that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> took two, three, and four <hi>per Cent,</hi> for owning Ships and though it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to avoid confiſcating them, yet theſe are the Ships which make ſuch a noiſe in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>To which the Lords of the Committee upon ſerious Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, by way of Anſwer repreſented to the King, That their Sentiments of the matter were quite different from what was pretended by the <hi>French;</hi> for that they underſtood that when the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ships were carried into the Ports of <hi>France,</hi> many of the Mariners complain'd of ill Uſage, and ſome of <hi>Torment,</hi> their Papers being ſeiz'd, and their <hi>Perſons</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der reſtraint, till all the Examinations were ready prepar'd; and that then all their <hi>Writings</hi> were ſent up to the Privy Council at St. <hi>Germaines,</hi> where judgment was definitively given, and ſeldom any reaſons for the Condemnation men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd in the decree, and never any Appeal or Reviſion ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; and whether that were the Tenderneſs or the Juſtice pretended by the <hi>French,</hi> they could not tell: But they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal'd to the Ambaſſadour Monſieur <hi>Courtin</hi> himſelf, whether the Method of proceeding in <hi>England</hi> had not been quite otherwiſe; and therefore that the different Methods of Juſtice and Clemency in <hi>England,</hi> might have entitled His Majeſty to a different acknowledgment, and more advantageous ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects from the <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That as to the latter part of the Paper, it ſeem'd to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain very harſh Imputations upon the Trade of His Majeſty's Subjects; and that only from ſome ill practices perhaps found out, general Rules were made, which having enter'd the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:43542:16"/> Thoughts of ſome Eminent Miniſters, that wonder'd that notwithſtanding the frequent and multiply'd Recommendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his Majeſty for Juſtice, the event of the <hi>French</hi> Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als ſhould prove ſo unfortunate; that if his Majeſty would but caſt his Eye upon the Cauſes annex'd, he would ſoon ſee.</p>
            <p>Whether, as it was imputed, all the Ships taken were <hi>Dutch</hi> Built.</p>
            <p>Whether they were all ſuch as never were in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether all the Maſters and Mariners were <hi>Dutch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether the Cockets were for Perſons unknown, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes not nam'd.</p>
            <p>Whether in the whole Liſt there was any more then one Ship from <hi>Waterford,</hi> any more than ſix from the reſt of all <hi>Ireland,</hi> or ſo much as one from <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether it were credible that all the Ships Company ſhould ſwear they were bound for <hi>Holland,</hi> when ſo many were taken coming from <hi>Holland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the other ſide, His Majeſty would find in the Liſt how many were <hi>Engliſh</hi> Built, taken with <hi>Engliſh</hi> Colours, <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Mariners, <hi>Engliſh</hi> Owners; ſome of them known to His Majeſty, and to whom the beſt Papers His Majeſty could ſign, or the Treaties requir'd were given all in vain.</p>
            <p>So that if the Caſe were in the General quite different from what in the General is repreſented, they hop'd it was no crime for His Majeſty's Subjects to make ſome noiſe in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> when they are Damnified, and ſee their Goods taken from them by Violence, and that Violence rather juſtifi'd than redreſs'd by Law.</p>
            <p>Wherefore conſidering that the Root of all theſe Diſorders aroſe from the Violence and Rapine of the <hi>French</hi> Capers, who were to be lookt upon as Diſturbers of the Publick Quiet, and Enemies of the Good Friendſhip between the two Crowns; they were humbly of Opinion that His <hi>Majeſty</hi> had juſt Occaſion from the injuries paſt, and thoſe which were then depending, and which every day increas'd, to make a ſerious Repreſentation of all to the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King, and not only to preſs for ſome better Method of repairing the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43542:16"/> Greivances mentioned, but to inſiſt upon the calling in of all the <hi>French</hi> Privateers; or elſe that His Majeſty ought to doe right, and give defence to his Subjects, from all the inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies which they ſo frequently met with. This was ſign'd.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Angliſey</item>
               <item>Bath</item>
               <item>Craven</item>
               <item>J. Ernle</item>
               <item>Finch C.</item>
               <item>Bridgewater</item>
               <item>H. Coventry</item>
               <item>G. Carteret</item>
            </list>
            <p>I might here add the Liſt it ſelf, by which it plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that, contrary to Monſieur <hi>Colbert</hi>'s Allegations, the Ships ſo taken were all either <hi>Engliſh</hi> Built, or Foreigners made Free, fraighted by <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants, own'd by <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Men, and mann'd with <hi>Engliſh,</hi> with Cockets and Bills of Lading to <hi>Engliſh.</hi> But 'tis ſufficient for me to ſhew, that the Miniſters and the Maſters are <hi>Chriſtians</hi> alike, <hi>Plunderers</hi> and <hi>Robbers,</hi> not only of Imperial Territories and Royal Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, but <hi>Beaſts</hi> of Prey, that turn the Seas into a Deſart, to gorge their voracious Appetites upon the Eſtates of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Perſons; and that upon the Account their <hi>Injuſtice</hi> and <hi>Rapines</hi> ſo wickedly and unjuſtly practiſed upon the People of <hi>England,</hi> no Nation under Heaven can have reaſons more allowable on their ſide to juſtifie a War with <hi>France,</hi> than <hi>England</hi> has, for the many <hi>Diſhonours, Injuries,</hi> and <hi>Affronts</hi> ſo ungratefully done us, in recompence of all the Kindneſs and great Services done them from time to time.</p>
            <p>For what greater kindneſs could there be, than to furniſh the <hi>Aſpiring Monarch</hi> with a continually recruited body of Ten Thouſand of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Youth, whoſe daring Bravery and Courage made oftentimes a Rape upon Victory it ſelf, to force her on his ſide, and reſcu'd once his whole Army from deſtruction; when in conſternation, and purſu'd by the Imperaliſts, upon the fall of <hi>Turenne?</hi> Yet when by the importunity of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> they were recall'd out of his ſervice, inſtead of fairly diſmiſſing them, well pay'd, for <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirk</hi> or <hi>Calais,</hi> from thence to croſs over for <hi>Dover,</hi> which
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:43542:17"/> was their direct Way; they were ſent through <hi>Burgundy,</hi> through <hi>Liomois,</hi> and ſo through the Provinces that lead to the Ports of <hi>Guyenne,</hi> that ſo the <hi>French</hi> might have time to debauch the Officers and Soldiers. In ſhort, the Soldiers who ſince their being in <hi>France,</hi> had been accuſtom'd to drink Wine, finding themſelves in a Country where it was almoſt as plentifull as Water, would not croſs the Sea to go home and drink Beer, but took pay under the Captains of the <hi>French</hi> Army in <hi>Catalonia,</hi> who were for that purpoſe poſted in their way. As for ſuch of the Officers as had nothing to loſe in their own Country, they were likewiſe debauch'd after the ſame manner, and diſpers'd at the ſame time in the Regiment of <hi>Fuſtenburgh,</hi> which was in the Garriſon of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pignan:</hi> So that when the <hi>Engliſh</hi> arriv'd at the Place where they were to Embark, they were not the Tenth of what they ſhould have been, had <hi>France</hi> dealt faithfully in the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs.</p>
            <p>Thus we have run through the Treacheries and Infidelities of the <hi>French</hi> in reference to <hi>England.</hi> There is no Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but much more might have been ſaid; however, here is enough to ſhew that there can be no ſafety in the friendſhip of a Prince, who makes it his ſtudy to be injurious in all his Actions, and faithleſs in all his Promiſes: <hi>Mendaciis &amp; falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciis tanquam praeclaris Artibus gaudens.</hi> But ſuch is the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief of that pernicious Vice, deſire of too much Glory, that it conſtrains a Man to be perfidious, as it was ſaid of <hi>Cneus Domitius; Nimiae Gloriae Cupiditas perfidum exiſtere coegit.</hi> And this was a Maxim among the Ancients, that Fidelity, like the Soul, when it has once left a Man, never returns again: And therefore with ſuch a one, <hi>Bellum ſuſpecta Pace tutius eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let us look Abroad, where we ſhall find the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> of Princes, ſtradling over <hi>Violations</hi> of <hi>Oaths</hi> by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Name, call'd <hi>Perjuries,</hi> and all the Laws and Bounds of Juſtice which God and Man have provided againſt the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undations of Violence, to graſp the Univerſal Monarchy of <hi>Europe.</hi> There you ſhall find him Invading, Burning, Spoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:43542:17"/> Plundring, Sacking, and Depopulating the Territories and Dominions of his Peaceable <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Neighbours, <hi>hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> out his way through the Bowels of Chriſtendom to the Imperial Throne; and all this under <hi>Claims</hi> and <hi>Pretenſions,</hi> abjur'd by all the moſt Solemn Renunciations that Religion could invent. Yet in Re-vindication of thoſe Claims and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſumed Rights ſo religiouſly renounc'd, like another <hi>Parenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus abominatus Hannibal,</hi> filling all with <hi>Bloud, Maſſacre</hi> and <hi>Devaſtation</hi> to Tyrannize over waſted Ruines, Cities laid Deſolate; and deſart Mountains, rather than not to Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannize at all. Where he could not enter with his Sword, he open'd a Paſſage with his <hi>Gold</hi> for ſubſervient Treachery, and the <hi>Foundations</hi> of future Miſchief into the Courts of moſt of the Princes of <hi>Europe;</hi> deflouring the Fidelity of their Counſellers, and <hi>raviſhing</hi> the Allegiance of their moſt Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Intimates, as if there had been a kind of Omnipotency in the Power of <hi>France</hi> to make Treachery and Falſhood Ubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitary.</p>
            <p>Perhaps this may be thought a little too ſevere; but this is not a time to Complement the <hi>Publick Enemy</hi> of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. This is a Seaſon to ſpeak out, ſince the wellfare of <hi>England</hi> is involv'd in the Common Fate of <hi>Europe.</hi> It is the Buſineſs of <hi>England</hi> to evidence how the <hi>French</hi> have violated the Law of Nations, which is common to all; and how they have labour'd to introduce ſuch <hi>Maxims</hi> into the World, as would deſtroy even the whole commerce of Mankind, and render Humane Societies no leſs Dangerous than a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>Tygers, Bears,</hi> and <hi>Lyons.</hi> Nor is <hi>England</hi> leſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd to defend the Publick Faith of Treaties againſt the crafty Eluſions and Quaint Evaſions of the <hi>French,</hi> and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move out of the ſight of Chriſtendom ſuch Scandalous Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, which, by conſequences no leſs fatal than unavoidable, would expoſe the Weakeſt to the Predominant Will and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the ſtrongeſt, and eſtabiſh Force, the Grand Arbitrator of all the Proceedings and Affairs of the World. It is the Buſineſs of <hi>England,</hi> in confederacy with Foreign Princes for the General Wellfare of Chriſtendom, to betake Her ſelf to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:43542:18"/> ſuch means and courſes, as may put a ſtop to a rapid Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent againſt the Impetuoſity, of which no Ties of Treaty, Marriage, Oaths, Bloud, Kindred, Friendſhip, or Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſion, can be Mounds and Bulwarks ſtrong enough to keep it within its Chanel. It is the Buſineſs of <hi>England,</hi> as far as in Her lies, to defend the common Intereſt of all Princes and States againſt a Prodigious Deſign; which for its Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, has nothing but an Exorbitant deſire of Conqueſt; no other End, than only Dominion; no other Means, but force of Arms and Treacherous Policy; nor any other Bounds, but what Chance and Fortune will be pleasd to preſcribe. Laſtly, It is not only the Buſineſs, but alſo for the Glory of <hi>England</hi> at this time, to recover Her former <hi>Grandeur;</hi> and as She was wont to doe, ſo at this time to decide the Fortune of <hi>Europe,</hi> and pronounce the Sentence either of Her Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom or Slavery: For between theſe two, there is no Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um to be expected, nor Peace to be ſecur'd. <hi>England</hi> for a long time has lain in a profound Lethargy, and therefore it is high time for Her now to awake, and put Her helping hand to prevent the Misfortunes and Calamities to which all <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> is expos'd by the prevailing Tyrannies and Oppreſſion of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are then in the next place to conſider how like a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King has dealt with the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> his Brother, His Friend, and Allie, after a Peace the moſt Solemnly concluded and ratified, after the moſt Sacred man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that could be imagin'd. Certainly the Calamities, the Miſeries, the Murthers, Rapines and Devaſtations, and Innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable Impieties that attend on War, are ſo diſagreeable from the Principles of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion, that nothing ought to be more Seriouſly, more Moderately, and more Warily conſider'd than the Juſtice of undertaking it: And therefore ſaid <hi>Herennius,</hi> Captain of the <hi>Samnites,</hi> having enter'd into a War againſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> after all that could be done to procure Peace, <hi>Rerum humanarum maximum Momentum eſt; quam propitiis, quam adverſis agant diis.</hi> Nor did he juſtifie the War upon any other grounds, than that his Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:43542:18"/> were conſtrain'd to it, and had no other hope but in their Arms. <hi>Juſtum eſt Bellum, Samnites, quibus neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, &amp; pia Arma, quibus nulla niſi in Armis relinquitur ſpes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Romans,</hi> though too blame perhaps in the <hi>Samnite</hi> War, (for which they dearly paid, and well it might be wiſh'd the <hi>French</hi> might pay as dearly for what they have done,) generally never enter'd into a War, but they ſet forth the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of their Reſentment, which for the moſt part was in revenge of their Allies, or to ſuccour their Friends and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates. Thus the firſt <hi>Punick</hi> War was to ſuccour <hi>Meſſana</hi> in <hi>Sicily,</hi> beſieg'd by the <hi>Carthaginians.</hi> The ſecond in revenge of <hi>Saguntum,</hi> ſack'd by <hi>Hannibal,</hi> contrary to the League between the two Common-wealths. And the third alſo for Reaſons of the ſame Nature: And ſo cautious they were to avoid the Scandal of being thought to make War, merely out of an Ambitious deſire to extend their Dominions, that after they had vanquiſh'd and reduc'd the <hi>Rhodians,</hi> who had taken part with <hi>Perſeus</hi> in the <hi>Macedonian</hi> War, they let them go unpuniſh'd: <hi>Ne quis divitiarum magis quam injuriae Bellum incoeptum diceret.</hi> And the ſame Author ſays, that in all the <hi>Punick</hi> Wars, after the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> had committed many nefarious Acts and Breaches of Faith to their Detriment, they never took any occaſion to doe the like; <hi>Magis quod ſe dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num foret, quam quod in illos jure fieri poſſet quaerebant:</hi> So that occaſions of enlarging their Dominions were rather of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd than ſought for by that Victorious Common-wealth. And it is obſervable, that the Ceremonies of denouncing War that were firſt inſtituted by <hi>Ancus Martius,</hi> the Heathen King of the <hi>Romans,</hi> were perform'd as Religiouſly, and with equal Soleminty to the Ceremonies of their Divine Worſhip. For when the <hi>Fecial</hi> came to the confines of the Country, againſt which the War was intended, <hi>Audi Jupiter,</hi> he cry'd; <hi>Audite Fines, Audiat Fas:</hi> Hear O <hi>Jupiter,</hi> Hear O ye Confines, hear Right and Juſtice: <hi>I am the Publick Meſſenger of the People of</hi> Rome, <hi>and come a Fecial, juſtly and piouſly ſent, and let Faith be given to my Words.</hi> After that, having made his demands, he again calls <hi>Jupiter</hi> to Witneſs, and thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:43542:19"/> 
               <hi>Si ego injuſte, impieque illos homines illaſque res dedier Nuncio Populi Romani Expoſco, tum Patriae Compotem me nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ſinas eſſe;</hi> if ſatisfaction were not given by the Prince or People to whom he was thus ſent within three and thirty days, the <hi>Fecial</hi> return'd again, and denounc'd War after this manner. <hi>Audi Jupiter, &amp; tu Juno, Quirine, Diique om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes coeleſtes voſque terreſtres, voſque inferni audite; Ego vos teſtor Populum iſtum injuſtum eſſe, neque jus perſolvere,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thus the more noble <hi>Heathen Romans,</hi> before they invaded the Borders of their Enemies, invok'd the Gods to Witneſs the Juſtice of their Cauſe, and the Wrongs and Injuries of thoſe that had incens'd them to take Arms. On the other ſide, the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King not regarding either God or Man, unexpected, unprovok'd, nay, after he had given aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurances that he had no ſuch deſign in his thoughts, <hi>thunder'd</hi> into his Neighbours Territories, under the Protection of League and Amity; and like a ſudden Tempeſt, with Sword and Fire, levels all before him.</p>
            <q>Burgundos Fraude Petivit</q>
            <p>Such an Ignoble and Unprincelike way of entring into Hoſtility, as looks more like Robbing upon the High-way, than a generous Method of War: For that it was a <hi>baſe</hi> and <hi>ignominious</hi> ſurprizal againſt the Faith and Honour of a King, beſides the Breach of Treaty is apparent from two Circumſtances; the one that paſs'd at <hi>Paris</hi> between the <hi>French</hi> King himſelf, and the Marqueſs <hi>De la Fuente</hi> Extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Ambaſſadour from <hi>Spain,</hi> who being upon his return into <hi>Spain</hi> upon the Death of the Old King, and not a little apprehenſive and jealous, that the vaſt Preparations made in <hi>France,</hi> were intended againſt the Queen and the Young Prince, was very importunate with his Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, to give ſome new and greater Aſſurances to the Queen of <hi>Spain,</hi> of the reality and ſincerity of his Intentions, though it were but only to quiet and ſettle her mind, againſt all the contrary Advices ſhe receiv'd from all Parts. Upon which
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:43542:19"/> the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King with all poſſible Aſſeverations en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd his Faith and Royal Word to the Queen, in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of her Ambaſſadour, that he would religiouſly keep the Peace, and continue a moſt faithfull Friendſhip both to Her and her Son.</p>
            <p>Another circumſtance was that of the Arohbiſhop of <hi>Ambrun,</hi> who, after the <hi>French</hi> Army was already in the Field, and had poſſeſs'd <hi>Charleroy,</hi> ſome four or five days before the News of it came to <hi>Madrid,</hi> proteſted and vow'd in <hi>Verbo Sacerdotis,</hi> and by all that was Sacred among the Roman Catholicks, that his Maſter intended nothing leſs than what was reported of him, and that he would never break with the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> nor invade his Dominions as long as he was under Age. And when the March of the <hi>French</hi> Army, and the Hoſtilities which they committed, ſo little agreed with the Promiſes of the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King; anſwer was made that it was no Breach, but only a taking Poſſeſſion of what belong'd to him: But the only way to ſurprize Men, is to take them unprovided; and the only way to take them unprovided, is to ſwear with all the Aſſeverations imaginable, that you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver intend to doe them any harm. And this is one of the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Kings ways of making War upon his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, ſo far from giving them thirty three Days Notice of his coming, that he will hardly allow them thirty three Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes: But it is a meanneſs in a Prince inſtructed by ſo great a Tutor as <hi>Mazarine,</hi> to be a <hi>ſlave to his Word;</hi> for which reaſon <hi>Fides Gallica,</hi> is of late become <hi>Fides Punica,</hi> no ſooner given but as ſoon broken.</p>
            <p>True it is that the <hi>French Academy</hi> has been long endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to refine their Language, by leaving off the uſe of ſome obſolete Words, by introducing others of a new Coyn, and enriching it with ſeveral quaint Expreſſions of a freſher Date; but how they could alter the ſignification of Words, and call <hi>War</hi> by the name of <hi>Peace,</hi> is a thing not eaſie to be underſtood: And therefore it were to be wiſh'd, they would explain to the World what they mean by the word <hi>Rupture,</hi> and how they can make a violent Invaſion with Men and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:43542:20"/> great Guns, to agree with the Obſervation of a Treaty, which forbid all manner of Attempts by armed Force, and was ſtipulated and contracted to no other end, but to prevent them: That they would explain which way it is poſſible for Peace to conſiſt with the Fatal effects of War; and how it is to be imagin'd that wanting the Formality of a Herauld to Proclaim the Hoſtility, it ſhould loſe all its Terrors and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice; ſince moſt Men of ordinary Reaſon believe that to be a Rupture which oppoſes the very Eſſence and Being of the Peace, ranverſes the very Foundations, and diſcompoſes all the Harmony of it.</p>
            <p>Now the Cauſes that mov'd the two Crowns to make the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> League, <hi>were the deſires of the Welfare, repoſe and eaſe of their Subjects.</hi> The effect was, <hi>to put an end to the many miſchiefs of the War; to forget and extinguiſh all the Cauſes and Motives which occaſion'd the War; and to eſtabliſh a Sincere, Entire, and Durable Peace between the two Kings, and their Succeſſors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which was ranvers'd by the firſt Invaſion of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Netherlands,</hi> which diſturb'd the Welfare and repoſe of the People, renew'd the Publick Calamities, and rekindl'd all the Cauſes of the paſt Wars.</p>
            <p>But to come to Particulars, the abandoning of <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal</hi> was one of the eſſential Fundamentals of the Peace, without which it never could have been treated nor conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. In reference to this, the Sixtieth Article runs thus: <hi>For that His Majeſty,</hi> meaning the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King, <hi>hath foreſeen and fear'd, leſt ſuch an Engagement ſhould be an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurmountable Obſtruction to the concluſion of Peace; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, reduce the two Kings to the neceſſity of a parpetual War.</hi> And a little lower in the ſame Article, he goes on in theſe Words: <hi>Although in conſideration of the Peace,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the abſolute <hi>neceſſity his ſaid Moſt</hi> Chriſtian <hi>Majeſty</hi> has been in to <hi>perpetuate the War by the Rupture of the</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Treaty, <hi>which His Majeſty found to be unavoidable,</hi> in caſe he would <hi>have any longer inſiſted upon</hi> prevailing in that <hi>affair with His Catholick Majeſty,</hi> to have obtain'd <hi>other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, than ſuch as he offer'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:43542:20"/>
            <p>In the ſecond place, it is plain that the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> to ſhew how reſolv'd he was that <hi>France</hi> ſhould abandon <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal,</hi> rejected the <hi>French</hi> King's offering, beſides the places he was bound to reſtore by the preſent Treaty to his Catholick Majeſty; all the reſt of the Places and Conqueſts, generally made by his Arms, during the preceding War, provided that the Affairs of the Kingdom of <hi>Portugal</hi> might be left in the ſame condition as they were then, as by another part of the ſame Article it appears: So that when nothing elſe would doe, it was by the ſame Article concluded and promiſed as follows:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>His Majeſty will no farther meddle with that Affair, and obliges and engages Himſelf, and promiſes upon his Honour, and upon the Word of a King, for Himſelf and his Succeſſors, not to give unto the ſaid Kingdom of</hi> Portugal, <hi>either in General, or to any Perſons in particular, of what Dignity, State, Condition, or Quality ſoever they be, now or hereafter, any Help or Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence, Publick or Secret, Directly or Indirectly, of Men, Arms, Ammunition, Victuals, Ships, or Money, upon any pretence or any other thing whatever, either by Land or Sea, or in any other manner: As alſo, not to ſuffer that any Levies of Men be made in any parts of his Kingdom or Dominions; nor to grant Paſſage to any that may come from other States, to the Aſſiſtence of the ſaid Kingdom of</hi> Portugal.</p>
            <p>One would think that nothing could have been more au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentickly expreſſed, or in terms more clear or more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, beyond the power of <hi>Nicety</hi> to find a flaw, or to make any other interpretation of the words, contrary to the ſenſe and meaning of the Parties at that time. And yet the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King found out a way to fail in all the Points, and all the circumſtances of his Promiſe: For notwithſtanding his <hi>Honour,</hi> and <hi>the Word of a King,</hi> before the Treaty was ſign'd, Cardinal <hi>Mazarine,</hi> ſent privately the Marqueſs of <hi>Cheaſes</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Portugal,</hi> to aſſure them, that tho' in order to the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Treaty then on foot with <hi>Spain,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> were forc'd to leave them out, and to engage not to aſſiſt them; yet, whatever they promis'd, they would never forſake them,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:43542:21"/> but would ſtill protect them againſt <hi>Spain,</hi> as they had done before: And they kept their word with <hi>Portugal,</hi> becauſe it was to the prejudice of <hi>Spain.</hi> To which purpoſe, the Peace was no ſooner concluded, but they ſuffer'd ſeveral Bands of Soldiers ſecretly to convey themſelves into <hi>Portugal;</hi> which being complain'd of by the Marqueſs <hi>De la Fuente,</hi> ſuch was the <hi>Punic</hi> Faith of <hi>France,</hi> that openly they ſent Publick Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to the Governours of their Ports, not to ſuffer any Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to embark for <hi>Portugal,</hi> but underhand gave them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Orders to let them paſs by way of connivance. Soon after M. <hi>Turenne</hi> made publick levies of Men, for the relief of <hi>Portugal,</hi> which the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ambaſſador repreſenting to the Council of <hi>France,</hi> receiv'd a cold and ſcornfull anſwer, that it was a particular Act of Marſhall <hi>Turenne,</hi> wherein the Court was no way concern'd: Nor did the <hi>French</hi> ceaſe to furniſh the <hi>Portuguieſes</hi> with Corn, and all ſorts of War-like Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition and Proviſion. Moreover, Letters were intercepted by the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> by which they were aſcertain'd, that all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long after the Peace was concluded, the <hi>French</hi> fomented and encourag'd the obſtinacy of the <hi>Portuguieſes,</hi> and diverted them from accepting the advantageous conditions that were offer'd them, by animating them with the hopes of potent Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours, not only for their own defence, but alſo to carry an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive War into the heart of <hi>Spain.</hi> Other Letters were like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe intercepted, Written from the Arch Biſhop of <hi>Ambrun,</hi> and Monſieur <hi>Lienne</hi> confirming the continual correſpondence which was between them in favour of the <hi>Portugals:</hi> Nor was this all, for the D. of <hi>B.</hi> was preſently after the Treaty, ſent to lie with the <hi>French</hi> Fleet upon the Coaſt of <hi>Portugal,</hi> and ſtay'd there a whole Summer to ſecure the coming and landing of Proviſions and Ammunition, of which the <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guieſes</hi> were then in extream want; and this at the ſame time that the <hi>French</hi> offer'd to mediate an Accommodation between <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Portugal.</hi> Nor was it long after the concluſion of the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> Treaty, that Monſieur <hi>Colbert</hi> made ſeveral Voyages into <hi>Portugal,</hi> to encourage them againſt the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and to enter into ſecret Alliance with them: And ſometime after the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:43542:21"/> 
               <hi>Spaniards</hi> took a <hi>French</hi> Veſſel, wherein was found an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the ſuccours which <hi>France</hi> had ſent from time to time into that Kingdom; by which it appear'd, that <hi>France</hi> had paid at her own expence a ſtanding Army in <hi>Portugal,</hi> to ſupport a War againſt <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to compleat her Perfidy, at length ſhe concluded a League offenſive with that Kingdom, of which theſe were the principal Conditions: <hi>That they would be the Friends of each others Friends, and Enemies of each others Enemies,</hi> England <hi>only excepted: That</hi> France <hi>ſhould furniſh them with as many Men, as ſhould be neceſſary to carry an offenſive War into</hi> Spain, <hi>both by Sea and Land, and ſhould advance by way of Loan, the one half of the Pay for the maintenance of the</hi> Auxiliary <hi>Troops. That</hi> France <hi>moreover ſhould pay them every Year by way of Loan, the ſumm of 300000 Crowns, and that all the Ports which ſhould be taken from the</hi> Spaniards <hi>upon either Sea, ſhould be put into the hands of the</hi> French, <hi>and that they ſhould not treat either of Truce or League without joynt conſent. This League to continue Ten Years.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By ſo many ſeveral Inſtances, let all the World be judges how little <hi>credit</hi> there is to be given to the <hi>Punic Faith</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> or what any other Prince can expect from his <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> or his <hi>Promiſes</hi> in any matter whatſoever; who thus <hi>foully forfeited</hi> ſuch a moſt Solemn Engagement to the Crown of <hi>Spain.</hi> For that a Treaty carry'd on between two Princes in order to a Marriage, which is one of the moſt Solemn Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiations that can be handled among Men, and <hi>confirm'd</hi> by an <hi>Oath, ſanctifi'd</hi> with all the moſt ſacred Myſteries of Chriſtian Religion, for a punctual obligation of performance, ſhould be thus inhumanly <hi>violated,</hi> is not to be parallell'd by any Example or Inſtance in Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>That noble example of the Roman Conſuls, who bid <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> not to fear, the Publick Faith ſecur'd him, is a thing of late unknown in <hi>France,</hi> where there is no ſecurity or truſt in the Honour or Royal Promiſe of the Prince. For his truth to <hi>Portugal</hi> was only ſelf-intereſt, to ſupport the <hi>Portuguieſes</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Spain,</hi> as formerly the <hi>French</hi> were wont to league
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:43542:22"/> with <hi>Scotland</hi> againſt <hi>England;</hi> ſo that whether the Character of <hi>Amurath</hi> the firſt, Emperor of the <hi>Turks,</hi> who is ſaid to have been <hi>Homo fallax, qui datam fidem ex opportunitate pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferendi imprimis metiebatur, bella &amp; pace ſimulato Egregius,</hi> may not fitly be apply'd to the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King, is left for them to determine who have felt the ſmart of his <hi>broken Leagues;</hi> which brings us to the ſecond Breach of the <hi>Pyre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naean</hi> Treaty. It is ſaid, and acknowledg'd by the <hi>Plenipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiaries</hi> in <hi>33d.</hi> Article of that Treaty, that the particular Capitulation of Marriage between the <hi>French</hi> King and the Eldeſt Daughter of <hi>Spain,</hi> bearing date with the General Treaty, was of the ſame force and vigor with the Treaty of Peace, as being the chiefeſt part thereof, and the moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, as well as the greateſt and moſt precious Earneſt of the ſecurity of its Duration.</p>
            <p>The Queen Mother of <hi>France,</hi> and Aunt to the <hi>Infanta,</hi> deſiring nothing more than the happy and ſuitable Union of two Perſons that were ſo dear in her Affection, to remove all impediments, and diſpell the doubts and ſcruples of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Counſel; found out an expedient, that by the contract of Marriage, the <hi>Infanta</hi> ſhould abſolutely renounce all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Right or Claim, which ſhe might for ever have to the whole, or any parts of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Succeſſion under any Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence or Title whatever, to the end the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Monarchy might in no caſe be liable, either to Foreign Subjection, or to be Diſmember'd: And they were more inclinable on both ſides to this expedient, becauſe the way had been open'd for them before by the Example of the Queen-Mother, whoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation was of the ſame Nature with the <hi>Pyrenaean,</hi> both in form and ſubſtance, and grounded upon the ſame incompati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of the two Succeſſions.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>Spain</hi> believing the ſame ſincerity in others as in himſelf, hearken'd to the offer, and thought that with ſuch a precaution he might reconcile the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Law with the <hi>Salique,</hi> and fully ſecure the Liberty of his Subjects. <hi>France</hi> on the other ſide acknowledg'd the thing to be <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>uſual,</hi> and freely conſented to it, for the ſake of the general good
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:43542:22"/> that ſhould reſult from ſuch a Peace, and confirm him in the poſſeſſion of ſo many conqueſts. Thereupon the Inſtrument was drawn up by conſent, and the <hi>French</hi> King oblig'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to ratifie it.</p>
            <p>Whence it is plain, that the <hi>Renunciation</hi> was an eſſential Member of the Peace, the very <hi>Soul</hi> and an inſeparable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the <hi>Treaty</hi> of <hi>Marriage,</hi> without which it never had been projected nor concluded, and conſequently neither the Treaty of Peace.</p>
            <p>Then again, that it was no private Act, but a Law and Pragmatick Sanction eſtabliſh'd by joynt conſent of the two Crowns, is as clear from the words of the Act it ſelf; <hi>And in the fifth and ſixth Articles of the ſaid Treaty, it has been decreed and reſolv'd by joynt conſent,</hi> that is to ſay, of the two Kings; <hi>and with one will, after ſerious conſideration,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that both my ſelf, and the Children which God ſhall give me by this Marriage, are and ſhall remain uncapable, diſabl'd, and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely excluded from any right or hope to ſucceed in any of the Kingdoms, States, Signiories,</hi> &amp;c. And a little lower, conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending to this with the joint deſire and earneſt wiſhes of their Subjects, Vaſſals, and Natives, who deſire <hi>that it may have the force and vigour of a Law and Pragmatick Sanction, and that it may be receiv'd and obſerv'd as ſuch;</hi> and ſome lines low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the following Section, are added theſe words: <hi>And it ſhall be decreed, by joynt conſent, that it is their Majeſties Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that this Act ſhall have the force and vigour of a Law E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh'd in favour of their Kingdoms, and the publick intereſts of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A little above the three moving cauſes are ſpecifi'd; <hi>And in regard it concerns the Publick State of both Crowns, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo large, they may never come to be united together, and to prevent all occaſions that may happen of joyning them,</hi> &amp;c, which is more fully explain'd two Pages lower. <hi>And having joyntly regard to the Publick and Common Good of the Kingdoms,</hi> which God has entruſted him with, which together with theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> are equally intereſted in this; that the <hi>Grandeur</hi> and <hi>Majeſty</hi> which they have upheld
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:43542:23"/> and maintain'd for ſo many Years together, with ſo much Happineſs and Glory to the renown of their Kings, may not be diminiſh'd nor fall to decay, as of neceſſity they will diminiſh and fall, if by the means and cauſe of this <hi>Marriage,</hi> they ſhall happen to unite and be joyn'd together in any one of the Children and Succeſſors; the ill conſequences whereof would cauſe ſuch diſcontents and afflictions to the Subjects, as ought to be conſider'd: Then the cauſes of the Renunciation are expreſs'd to be the <hi>publick good</hi> of the Kingdoms, the preſervation of the <hi>Grandeur,</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> of their Majeſties; to prevent the diſcontents of the People, and the Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences which might otherwiſe ariſe, and to facilitate for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the Marriages between the Children and Succeſſors of the two Princes. All which cauſes being in their own nature <hi>unal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable,</hi> and of neceſſity abſolute, could not be faſten'd upon any particular Act, nor limited to any teſtrictive conditions.</p>
            <p>This League therefore thus grounded upon theſe Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, were ſuch Limitations and bounds to a Perſon aſpring to the Univerſal Monarchy of <hi>Europe,</hi> as were not to be fenced in with the common Ties and reſtraints of <hi>Oaths</hi> and Treaties. And therefore ſo ſoon as the Old King of <hi>Spain</hi> was <hi>dead,</hi> the <hi>French Lawyers,</hi> well underſtanding the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of their Sovereign, and preferring the little <hi>Quirks</hi> of <hi>Law</hi> before the <hi>Publick Faith</hi> ſtarted up a claim for their King in the right and behalf of his Wife the <hi>Infanta,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding her <hi>Solelmn Renunciation,</hi> which was made a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the body of the Treaty, and as ſacredly ſworn to by the <hi>French</hi> King himſelf; pretending that a great part of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Low Countries was devolv'd to him in her Right by the Municipal Laws, and Local Cuſtoms of thoſe Countries. Whereas it is a thing well known, that when Sovereign Princes enter into Treaties (which are indeed the true and only Laws between Monarchs) they are regulated and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd according to the Law of Nations common to all; and being ſo to be underſtood, it is an idle thing for <hi>Civilians</hi> to imagin, that a conſideration of Laws Municipal, or cuſtoms belonging to any particlar Country, under the Dominion of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:43542:23"/> either of the Treating Princes, can be admitted to the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing of a Treaty, or the depriving either of the Parties of the Benefit and Security which he has thereby.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding the <hi>Renunciation</hi> was ſo carefully Penn'd, as if a whole Grand Council of <hi>Civil Lawyers</hi> had been call'd to out-doe all former Terms and expreſſions us'd in ſuch Contracts, and to find out new binding Clauſes; to prevent all poſſibility of Evaſion, the <hi>French</hi> King was more eaſily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to believe that his own great <hi>Cannon-Law</hi> was above all other <hi>Law,</hi> and more conſentaneous to his Reaſon and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Deſigns; and therefore againſt the very ſenſe and end of the <hi>Renunciation,</hi> under the ſlight pretence of a <hi>Non-Entity,</hi> he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took himſelf to force and violence, and with a powerfull Army fell on a ſudden upon <hi>Flanders,</hi> and other parts of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Territories, with ſuch an Inundation of War, that it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for the unprovided <hi>Spaniard</hi> to reſiſt him; more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, after ſuch deep Aſſeverations, that all his vaſt Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations were no way intended againſt the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Dominions.</p>
            <p>Theſe proſperous ſucceſſes occaſioned the <hi>Triple League,</hi> which put a ſtop to the <hi>French</hi> Career, and brought on ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Treaty,</hi> which was manag'd at <hi>Aken,</hi> or <hi>Aix la Chappell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> in order to a new Agreement between <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain.</hi> The Obſervation of which affords us another inſtance of that ye call <hi>French Fidelity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this Treaty the <hi>French</hi> King was to remain poſſeſs'd of <hi>Charleroy, Binch, Athe, Doway,</hi> the Fort of <hi>Scarp, Turnay, Oude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard, Lille, Armentiers, Courtray, Bergues,</hi> and <hi>Turnes,</hi> and all their <hi>Bayliwicks,</hi> &amp;c. and reſtore to the King of <hi>Spain</hi> the County of <hi>Burgundy</hi> together with <hi>Aloſt.</hi> And to this <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> all the Princes of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> were invited to give the two Kings their <hi>Promiſes</hi> and <hi>Engagements</hi> of <hi>Warranty,</hi> as to all the Contents of the <hi>Treaty.</hi> And by another Article of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it was accorded, that whatever ſhould on the day of the <hi>Ratification</hi> of the <hi>Peace</hi> be found upon the <hi>Lands</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> ſhould appertain to Her, and that whatever in like manner ſhould be found upon the <hi>Lands</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> ſhould appertain to the Crown of <hi>Spain;</hi> but, as if it were an impoſſibility for
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:43542:24"/> 
               <hi>France</hi> to keep her word, the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Prince deſigning to make his Advantage of this Article, before the Ratificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on came, caus'd the <hi>Ax</hi> to be ſet to a <hi>Wood</hi> of <hi>Overgrown Trees,</hi> which was upon the <hi>Lands</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> and having fell'd the Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, tranſported it into his own Dominions, that when the <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification</hi> ſhould come, he might have an excuſe for what he had done.</p>
            <p>In like manner, though he were to reſtore all <hi>Burgundy</hi> by the <hi>Articles</hi> of this <hi>Treaty</hi> without reſervation, and though he were Sworn upon the Croſs, the Holy Evangeliſts, the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of the Maſs, and upon his Honour, fully, really, and <hi>bona fide</hi> to obſerve and accompliſh all the contents of the Articles: yet he both diſmantl'd the ſtrong Holds and Places of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, carryed away all the Ammunitions and Warlike Proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and would have deſtroyed the Rich Salt Pits of that <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince,</hi> but for the powerfull Interpoſition of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor could this Treaty of <hi>Aix,</hi> ſo religiouſly ſworn to tie up the <hi>French</hi> King from exacting heavy Contributions from the Ducheſs of <hi>Lymburgh</hi> and <hi>Luxenburgh,</hi> from laying new claims to ſome Towns as important as any of thoſe that had been granted him by the Peace; nor from confiſcating the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of the Subjects of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> that refus'd to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwear their Allegiance, not ſparing the Royal Houſe of <hi>Mary Mont.</hi> And as if theſe Infractions and Incroachments had not been ſufficient, they forc'd their way with great Quantities of Merchandize through the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Territories, without paying Cuſtoms, and not long after enveavour'd to ſurprize the Town of <hi>Hainault.</hi> And in ſhort, they did whatever they pleas'd, plunder'd even the moſt ſacred Places, and acted without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morce or pitty, whatever can be imagined by inſolent and unconſcionable Men.</p>
            <p>This perfidious dealing of <hi>France</hi> with <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> ſpreading over <hi>Europe</hi> like a Gangrene, as it prov'd extreamly prejudicial to ſome, ſo it became no leſs pernicious to others of the <hi>Europaean</hi> Princes.</p>
            <p>Among the reſt, the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> by the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:43542:24"/> Treaty, was to be reſtor'd to his Dukedom of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> with all the Places and Towns which he had poſſeſſed in the Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks of <hi>Mets, Toul,</hi> and <hi>Verdun.</hi> But <hi>France,</hi> after the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eution of the other Articles of that Peace, delay'd as long as ſhe could the performance of that part which related to the Duke, and ſtill refus'd to reſtore him to his Country, till ſhe had made him condeſeend to another <hi>Treaty</hi> with her, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he was conſtrain'd to part with ſeveral other conſiderable Places, beſides what had been granted to him by the <hi>General Peace.</hi> Nor would that Uſurpation ſatisfie her voracious Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite; for that after a Year and an half of an unſettl'd Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, during which time, under ſeveral unjuſt pretences, new quarrells were every day pick'd with him, till ſhe forc'd him with a conſiderable Army, to ſurrender into her hands his Town of <hi>Marſul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor was it long after before the <hi>French</hi> again compell'd him to ſign a new <hi>Treaty,</hi> ſtill more diſadvantageous than the two former; nor could he then, as little as before, have any quiet Enjoyment of that little they had left him, till they had worm'd him out of all. For every day the <hi>French</hi> encroached upon his <hi>Juriſdiction,</hi> the Liberties of his <hi>Territories,</hi> and his <hi>Sovereign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> it ſelf: He laid moſt <hi>Enormous Taxes</hi> upon the Duke's Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; he conſtrain'd him to disband his <hi>Forces,</hi> and then to raiſe new <hi>Men</hi> again, as the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Uſurper thought fit. He was kept from revenging his own Quarrels, to take part in that of others, all his Enemies were let looſe againſt him, to ſtop the progreſs of his Armies, as ſoon as he had gain'd the leaſt Advantage. And in few Words, the Noble Duke, who deſerv'd a much better <hi>Treatment,</hi> was all that while rather a <hi>Vaſſal</hi> to <hi>France,</hi> than a <hi>Sovereign Prince.</hi> Neither would this ſatisfie the Ambition of the <hi>French</hi> King, who fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by many circumſtances how highly the Duke reſented ſuch <hi>Deſpotick <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage,</hi> he ſent one of his Generals to ſurprize and ſeize his <hi>Perſon,</hi> and to bring him either dead or alive. A new <hi>French Mode</hi> of dealing with Sovereign Princes, not known in the more generous Climates of <hi>Europe,</hi> and which may give us ſome Hopes of ſeeing the <hi>Northern</hi> part of the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:43542:25"/> World govern'd by <hi>Baſha</hi>'s as well as the <hi>Eaſtern.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But 'tis an infallible <hi>Maxim,</hi> that every Prince diſpoſſeſs'd of his Eſtate, may hold for certain there will be nothing omitted on the Uſurper's part, or Conquerer in Poſſeſſion, to ruin him if poſſible, and all his Generation. Therefore 'tis not ſtrange that the <hi>French</hi> King ſhould leave no Stone unturn'd for the Deſtruction of His Highneſs of <hi>Lorrain:</hi> From hence it was, that the <hi>Imperial Governour</hi> of <hi>Philipsburgh,</hi> the ſame who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards baſely and cowardly ſurrender'd up that Garriſon to <hi>Crequi,</hi> ſo notoriouſly and openly as he did, attempted the Deſtruction of that Prince, by a <hi>Trap-door</hi> which he cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly caus'd to be contriv'd for that purpoſe in the <hi>Bridge</hi> of that Place; through which the Duke, not dreaming of any ſuch <hi>French</hi> Treachery ſo near him, fell head long to the Bottom of the <hi>Ditch.</hi> For may it not be juſtly inferr'd, that this <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour</hi> had capitulated and agreed with ſome Chriſtian Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of <hi>France,</hi> to execute ſo greatfull a peice of <hi>Treaſon,</hi> more eſpecially, ſince it was by the Power of the Favourers of <hi>France</hi> at <hi>Vienna,</hi> that the <hi>Traitors</hi> eſcap'd altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſh'd.</p>
            <p>And now we are come to <hi>Vienna,</hi> it will not be amiſs to take a ſhort view of the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King's behaviour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Emperor, where he will be found nothing chang'd either in his <hi>Morals</hi> or his <hi>Politicks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the occaſion that ever his <hi>Imperial Majeſty</hi> gave the <hi>French</hi> King, to make ſuch Bloudy Wars upon Him, there is no body that can tell of any: Nor is it probable that a Prince ſo good Natur'd, ſo Piouſly inclin'd, ſo much given to Repoſe, and Peace, and ſo averſe from contending with his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, or making War upon his Inferiours, as he is ſaid to be, ſhould be an <hi>Aggreſſor:</hi> But all the World knows that it has been long the <hi>Ambition</hi> of <hi>France</hi> to graſp in his hands the Univerſal <hi>Monarchy</hi> of the fourth part of the <hi>Habitable Earth;</hi> and this is that which makes the <hi>French</hi> King ſeek Occaſions of Publick Univerſal Diſturbance, and the better to ſucceed, to leave nothing unattempted that force or fraud can procure. It is no Quarrel between <hi>Nations,</hi> bearing enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:43542:25"/> to one <hi>another,</hi> neither is it in revenge of Injuries recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but an impotent <hi>Rage</hi> and <hi>Luſt</hi> of Empire in one Man, that has ſet all <hi>Europe</hi> together by the Ears; <hi>Delirat Ludovicus, plectitur Europa.</hi> One man is mad for the Empire, and that madneſs of one man ſets all <hi>Europe</hi> in a <hi>Flame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for that the worſt of Uſurpers would be thought to have ſome glittering pretence for their <hi>Injuſtice,</hi> therefore it is that the <hi>French</hi> King makes it his buſineſs, to find out men of <hi>Wit</hi> and <hi>Cavil,</hi> to turmoil for Juſtifications of his illegal Actions; ſuch men are eaſily found, and the Temptations of Gold makes them no leſs ſedulous to gratifie the <hi>Jupiter</hi> that commands the Golden Showres; ſo that if they can but find him a Pretence of Claim, he'll find Armies and Bombs to make it good. Under the warmth of ſuch Golden Encouragements was Hatch'd that Elaborate <hi>Peice,</hi> Entitled, <hi>The juſt Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the King</hi> (meaning the <hi>French</hi> King) to <hi>Europe;</hi> wherein after the Author has laid it for a Foundation, that the <hi>Demeſnes</hi> and Conqueſts of <hi>Kingdoms</hi> are always the <hi>Demeſnes</hi> and Conqueſts of <hi>Sovereigns,</hi> and that the Conqueſts and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſnes</hi> of Crowns cannot be aſcertain'd or preſcrib'd; he adds, <hi>That the greater part of</hi> Germany <hi>is the Patrimony and Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent inheritance of the</hi> French <hi>Kings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charlemaigne poſſeſs'd</hi> Germany <hi>not as Emperor, but as King of</hi> France. From which Doctrine it is evident, that his <hi>Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Majeſty,</hi> nor indeed any Prince in <hi>Europe,</hi> can ever be ſafe, nor hope for any quiet, while the <hi>Ambition</hi> of <hi>France</hi> is in a condition to lay ſuch a claim to their <hi>Dominions.</hi> More eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, ſince it is known by wofull experience, that the <hi>French</hi> King gives no other Reaſons for his unjuſt <hi>Violences,</hi> nor cares to give any other than what the <hi>Lyon</hi> gave to the weaker <hi>Beaſts;</hi> one part is his <hi>Right,</hi> as King of the <hi>Foreſt,</hi> another becauſe he is able to <hi>ſubdue;</hi> the third he takes by <hi>Force,</hi> and for the <hi>reſt,</hi> touch it who <hi>dares.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another Cunning, to ſet up a <hi>French</hi> Title is by the means of certain <hi>Scribes,</hi> as good as ever <hi>Granger,</hi> ſo dextrous at the ſtrokes of their <hi>Pens,</hi> that they will imitate the obſolete <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thick</hi> Characters with that exactneſs, that you would ſwear
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:43542:26"/> they were Written above Five or Six Hundred Years agoe, and by that means, they will ſet up a <hi>Dependence</hi> from ſuch a diſtance of time, that <hi>Beelzebub</hi> himſelf ſhall not be able to diſprove it.</p>
            <p>Upon theſe Foundations it was, that as if he were dealing only with the <hi>Farmers</hi> of his <hi>Revenues,</hi> by a Publick <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> he erected a Sovereign Court at <hi>Mets,</hi> compos'd accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the cuſtom of <hi>France,</hi> of a dozen of his Lawyers, who, by virtue of the King's Authority, and the Miniſtry of the <hi>Catchpoles</hi> of that clandeſtine Juriſdiction, ſummon before them all ſuch <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> as are poſſeſs'd of any Territory which the King is pleas'd to call a <hi>Dependence</hi> upon any State, with which he has nothing to doe; and when no body appears to acknowledge the Juriſdiction of this <hi>Tyrannical</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Piepoudre,</hi> and to give them an account by what Right they poſſeſs what their Predeceſſors have for three or four Hundred Years peaceably enjoy'd; preſently the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Prince makes his own Power his Judges and his Army his Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates, and immediately with <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Sword</hi> ſeizes upon the confiſcated <hi>Dominion.</hi> And by virtue of ſuch Pretenſions as theſe, he <hi>claims</hi> and has <hi>poſſeſs'd</hi> himſelf of the Dukedom of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> the Dutchy of <hi>Deux Ponts,</hi> and the beſt part of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatia,</hi> as being dependencies of the <hi>Biſhopricks</hi> of <hi>Toul, Metz,</hi> and <hi>Verdun;</hi> and conſequently muſt be united to the <hi>Demeſnes</hi> of the Crown of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having then ſo clear a Title to the <hi>Empire,</hi> no wonder he purſues ſo <hi>dreadfully</hi> the recovery of his Right. And yet the true Mother of the Child could not endure to ſee the Bowels of her <hi>Infant</hi> ript up before her Eyes; no, nor can we believe the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Prince to be the Hereditary Father of thoſe Countries, which, in deteſtation of all Compaſſion, he ſo inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manly <hi>ranſacks</hi> and <hi>depopulates;</hi> being then a Spurious Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, diſown'd by the <hi>Legitimate Parents</hi> of all true Titles, <hi>Law,</hi> and <hi>Juſtice,</hi> which only fraud and force could make good. Of both how dreadfully, and how too ſucceſsfully the <hi>Ambitious Monarch</hi> has made uſe in aſſerting his illegal claims, all <hi>Europe</hi> can too ſadly teſtifie; no leſs laviſh of his Gold than of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:43542:26"/> Bloud. The Grand <hi>Viſier,</hi> and the Cham of <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copite Tartary,</hi> were his <hi>Penſioners,</hi> dazl'd with ſeveral Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his <hi>Louiſian</hi> Medalls; the one to divert the Arms of <hi>Poland;</hi> the other to keep his <hi>Imperial Majeſty</hi> employ'd in the utmoſt Limits of his Dominions, bordering upon <hi>Turky,</hi> that he with the leſs reſiſtence might revel in the Ruins of the flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing <hi>Gardens</hi> and <hi>Cities</hi> of the <hi>Rhine.</hi> And as he tramples under foot all <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> at Home ſo by tampering with the Miniſters and Subjects of other Princes, he inſtructs them here to manage their fidelity to the beſt advantage of his own Ambition, and by a <hi>Metal</hi> of his own, tries what <hi>Metal</hi> they are made of before he deal with their Maſters. And with this ſort of <hi>White Powder,</hi> which does execution without Noiſe, ſhoots down more Citadels, Caſtles, and ſtrong Holds, and takes in more Towns than all the <hi>Thunder</hi> of his <hi>Cannon.</hi> In ſo much, that it has been obſerv'd, that when his Ambaſſadors go abroad, they either carry along with them the Principal <hi>Engins,</hi> or elſe they are ſent after them; an Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador, or an Agent go before his Army, and then uſually a Conqueſt follows. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is his <hi>Motto:</hi> A new way to Honour and Renown, unknown to <hi>Alexander,</hi> or any of the dull <hi>Roman</hi> Conquerors.</p>
            <p>Had not the Steward of Commiſſary General <hi>Capellier</hi>'s Houſe been tainted with this golden <hi>Poiſon,</hi> he had never been ſurpriz'd by his Maſter in the very Act of <hi>Traiterous Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence</hi> with the Miniſter of <hi>France,</hi> to whom he gave an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act accompt of all he could diſcover in his Maſter's Houſe. And to confirm what his Maſter had detected, at length cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Letters, which the Steward was to have received from the <hi>French</hi> Miniſter, were ſeiz'd at the Imperial <hi>Poſt-Office</hi> in <hi>Frankford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the Peace of <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> the City of <hi>Strasburgh</hi> thought it ſelf in full ſecurity, confirm'd by ſeveral <hi>fervent</hi> and <hi>vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> Letters, which the <hi>French</hi> King wrote to them from time to time, and the aſſurances given them by his Reſident abiding in the City, that his Maſter <hi>deſir'd</hi> nothing more than to live in Peace and Amity with the <hi>Emperor,</hi> and with the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:43542:27"/> Cities of the Empire. And yet by the <hi>underhand,</hi> conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and tampering with the ſame <hi>Reſident,</hi> a Traitor was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen <hi>Burghermaſter,</hi> who acted altogether conformable to the Advice of <hi>France.</hi> On the other ſide, the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> and <hi>Burgheſſes</hi> being lull'd aſleep by the fair Promiſes and Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>France,</hi> diſmiſs'd their Guard of <hi>Switzers,</hi> which were the chief ſecurity of their City: But no ſooner were the <hi>Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers</hi> departed, but <hi>Monſieur Louvoy</hi> with a powerfull Army inveſted the City, and forc'd them to ſurrender upon ſuch Conditions as he was pleas'd to preſcribe them. After which the <hi>French</hi> King made no ſcruple to violate thoſe pitifull <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> which they granted them, and to treat them as <hi>Slaves</hi> like the reſt of his Subjects.</p>
            <p>The Treaty of <hi>Nimeguen</hi> began in the Name of the moſt holy and indiviſible Trinity; and the end of it was, that there ſhould be an immoveable and unſhaken Peace between his <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Majeſty</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> King, to ſtop the <hi>deſolation</hi> of ſo many Provinces, and the Effuſion of ſo much <hi>Chriſtian Bloud;</hi> yet, no ſooner was the Emperor engag'd againſt the <hi>Turk,</hi> and that <hi>Spain</hi> and her Allies had laid down their Arms and disbanded the greateſt part of their Forces, relying upon the <hi>Faith</hi> of the Treaty of <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> but the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King fell in upon <hi>Flanders</hi> with a more than <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Fury, <hi>Burning, Plundring,</hi> and <hi>Levelling</hi> with the Earth whole <hi>Towns</hi> and <hi>Villages,</hi> on purpoſe to conſtrain the People to revolt, and to become his Vaſſals to preſerve themſelves from utter ruin.</p>
            <p>The Correſpondence of the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King with the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Port, is too well known, and how it was at his Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Importunity, that the Grand Seignior broke the firſt Truce which he had made with the Empire, to ſecond the deſigns of Count <hi>Teckeley.</hi> whom <hi>France,</hi> out of a particular Zeal to the <hi>Catholick Religion,</hi> aſſiſted with Men and Money, and that prevailing charm it was that wrought upon the Port to ſend back Count <hi>Caprara,</hi> and reject the Propoſitions of Peace which he carry'd along with him. Of which the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs of <hi>Seppeville,</hi> then the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſador at <hi>Viena,</hi> fail'd
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:43542:27"/> not with all diligence to give his Maſter Notice; who with no leſs ſedulity diſpatch'd another Perſon to the Grand Viſier, to oblige and encourage him to contrive the Seige of <hi>Vienna,</hi> urging him that it was for his Honour not to quit it; That the City was at its laſt Gaſp, and that it behov'd him to take it, whatever it coſt him, for the ſake of his Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the publick Good of the Port; for that the Seige having made ſuch a noiſe in the World, he could not leave the proſecution of it without Eternal Infamy to the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire, and the Grand <hi>Vizier;</hi> adding withall, that to facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the taking of the Town, and to divide the Emperors Forces, his Maſter would enter into <hi>Flanders</hi> with a Puiſſant Army, which would infallibly oblige the Princes of the <hi>Empire,</hi> to recall their Forces for their own Security. And in that point, he was as good as his Word to the <hi>Turk,</hi> entring <hi>Flanders</hi> at the ſame time with <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Sword,</hi> as if he had been ſecond to <hi>Mahomet.</hi> But when <hi>Vienna</hi> was reliev'd, he was ſo far from partaking in the general Joy of the reſt of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> World, that he forbid his <hi>Eccleſiasticks</hi> to obſerve any <hi>Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving</hi> for the <hi>Victory</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> upon pain of incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his High Diſpleaſure.</p>
            <p>Nor is it only by the aſſiſtence of open and profeſs'd <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels,</hi> that the <hi>French</hi> King fights the <hi>Emperor</hi> abroad, but by the means of his pretended <hi>Friends,</hi> and neareſt <hi>Counſellors,</hi> who having finger'd the <hi>Gold</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> become <hi>Traitors</hi> to their <hi>Lawfull Prince,</hi> and betray his very <hi>Cabinet Secrets.</hi> This occaſion'd the miſunderſtanding that happen'd between the Duke of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> and <hi>Montecuculi,</hi> General of the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Forces in the <hi>Holland</hi> War.</p>
            <p>For in the Year 1672. when all <hi>Europe</hi> look'd upon the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Provinces</hi> near the brink of <hi>Deſtruction,</hi> the Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> fore ſeeing the conſequences to be expected from the ſucceſsfull enterpriſes of <hi>France,</hi> took the Field with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Army, at what time <hi>Montecuculi</hi> was on his March, with a deſign to act jointly. Upon which <hi>Turenne</hi> was ſent to oppoſe thoſe two Armies, but by the ſeveral <hi>Marches</hi> and <hi>Counter Marches</hi> which the Elector made, <hi>Turenne's</hi> Army
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:43542:28"/> was ſo tir'd and harraſs'd, that about the end of the <hi>Campaigne</hi> it was in ſo miſerable a condition, that all <hi>Turenne</hi> could doe, was to defend himſelf; which caus'd the <hi>Elector</hi> to make a vigorus Remonſtrance of all things to be made to the <hi>Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Council.</hi> Which wrought ſo effectually, that poſitive Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders were ſent <hi>Montecuculi</hi> to join the Elector and fight <hi>Turenne,</hi> without farther loſs of time; ſo that nothing but <hi>Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> the mode of <hi>France,</hi> could have prevented the Total Ruine of <hi>Turenne's</hi> Army. But the <hi>French</hi> Inſtruments in the <hi>Imperial Court</hi> ſo order'd the matter, that <hi>Montecuculi's</hi> Orders were chang'd, and an expreſs command ſent him, neither to joyn the Elector, nor to fight <hi>Turenne.</hi> The Elector, who had receiv'd from the Court of <hi>Vienna</hi> a formal Letter, which gave him an Account of the true Order which the Emperor had ſent his <hi>General</hi> to joyn him, and fight the ſhatter'd Enemies, wonder'd when <hi>Montecuculi,</hi> being by him ſummond to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the Order, refus'd to obey it: But <hi>Montecuculi,</hi> who knew nothing of the Letter ſent the Elector, could do no leſs than follow his own Inſtructions.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Elector</hi> was concern'd in <hi>Reputation</hi> to make the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror</hi> ſenſible of <hi>Montecuculi's</hi> proceedings; and if <hi>Montecuculi</hi> was ſtrangely ſurpriz'd, when at his return to <hi>Vienna,</hi> his <hi>Imperial Majeſty</hi> call'd him to a ſtrict Account, why he nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther join'd the <hi>Brandenburgher,</hi> nor fought <hi>Turenne,</hi> the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror</hi> was no leſs amaz'd, when his General produced for his diſcharge an <hi>Order</hi> in exact form, forbidding him to doe either the one or the other. This was a perfect Myſtery, however, afterwards it was found out to have been a contrivance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>French Emiſſaries,</hi> and ſome of the <hi>Imperial Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> who having eaſily found a way to intercept the <hi>Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Order,</hi> and in the ſame Diſpatch to tranſmit a falſe one under a counterfeited Hand and Seal. And thus perhaps it was that <hi>General Souches,</hi> after the Battle of <hi>Senneff,</hi> drew off from the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and left him in the Lurch, under pretence of not having order to doe any more than what he had done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tarbrack</hi> was a Town upon the Borders of <hi>Germany,</hi> that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:43542:28"/> ſtood conveniently for the purpoſes of the <hi>French</hi> King, and therefore he reſolv'd to fortifie it. On the other ſide, the <hi>Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſts</hi> complain'd of it to the <hi>French</hi> King, as a Truce and Treaty both at one time; but all the Anſwer they could get, was, that the <hi>Royal Chamber</hi> of <hi>Mets</hi> had irrevocably decreed it to belong to the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> and therefore the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> had no reaſon to complain of a Sovereign <hi>Monarch's</hi> fortifying his Frontier Towns.</p>
            <p>His very propoſals of <hi>Marriage</hi> are only <hi>ſnares</hi> to entrap ſuch Princes as will accept of his <hi>Matches;</hi> and becauſe his main deſign is at the Empire, therefore he ſtrives to ſcatter his <hi>Circes</hi> and <hi>Medias</hi> among the Princes of <hi>Germany.</hi> Believing Wives to be the fitteſt Inſtruments to betray their Husbands, and the nuptial ſheets to be the ſecureſt <hi>Harbours</hi> for <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus after the Marqueſs of <hi>Bethune's</hi> Siſter was married to the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> jealouſies between the <hi>King</hi> her <hi>Husband</hi> and the <hi>Emperor</hi> were fomented, and Factions ſet up in that Country, by the means of thoſe <hi>Golden Rays</hi> which the Sun of <hi>France</hi> diſplays in that Court by the Hands of the <hi>Bankers</hi> of <hi>Hamburgh</hi> and <hi>Dantzick.</hi> And the more to encourage her to play her Gaime according to the <hi>French Inſtructions,</hi> his Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Majeſty made her Father a <hi>Duke</hi> and <hi>Peer</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and promis'd to receive her as a <hi>Queen,</hi> and not as a <hi>Subject,</hi> if ſhe return'd a <hi>Widow,</hi> in her own <hi>Country.</hi> Thus he thought to have caught the Young Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> with one of his natural <hi>Daughters;</hi> but that <hi>Heroick Prince</hi> deſpis'd the Motion. And if the <hi>French</hi> King were aſſur'd that the Young Prince of <hi>Poland</hi> ſhould ſucceed his Father, there is another natural <hi>Daughter</hi> of <hi>France</hi> ready prepar'd for him; for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, it would be a <hi>Daughter</hi> merely thrown away, if ſhe could not be in a Station to ſerve her own <hi>Country.</hi> For that the main end of the <hi>French</hi> King, in giving <hi>French</hi> Wives to the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and the ſeveral Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> is to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the ſtrength of the <hi>Empire,</hi> and leſſen the Authority of the <hi>Emperor,</hi> by ſeparating from his intereſt the particular Princes of the Empire by private <hi>Intrigues,</hi> and diſtinct
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:43542:29"/> 
               <hi>Treaties,</hi> which though it be contrary to the Treaty of <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> yet that ſignifies nothing to a Prince who has no ſuch <hi>Veneration</hi> for <hi>Leagues</hi> as to think them worth obſerving.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>French</hi> King's dealing with the Duke of <hi>Nieuburgh</hi> it was ſomewhat <hi>Barbarous;</hi> for that, after the <hi>French</hi> King had caus'd him to <hi>Mortgage</hi> the greateſt part of his <hi>Estate</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt beyond the hopes of <hi>Redemption,</hi> in expectation of the <hi>Poliſh Crown,</hi> to which <hi>France</hi> had promis'd to advance him by the aſſiſtence of a <hi>strong Party,</hi> which ſhe had in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, contrary to the <hi>Treaties,</hi> as well with the <hi>Duke</hi> as with the Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> and to his reiterated <hi>Promiſes</hi> and <hi>Vows,</hi> both by word of <hi>Mouth</hi> and in <hi>Writing;</hi> he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, by his <hi>Creatures</hi> and <hi>Agents,</hi> oppos'd the <hi>Duke</hi>'s preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and endeavoured with all the induſtry and importunity imaginable, to have the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> preferr'd before him, and all the reſt of his Competitors; a ſufficient warning to all Princes how they relie upon the <hi>broken Reed</hi> of <hi>French</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity.</p>
            <p>The Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> was environed with <hi>French Emiſſaries</hi> and <hi>Spies,</hi> and ſome of his Principal <hi>Ministers</hi> ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxicated with the Elixirs of <hi>France,</hi> that nothing was ſaid or done in his <hi>Palace,</hi> of which the <hi>French</hi> Envoy had not ſwift <hi>Intelligence.</hi> And the World was well inform'd of all the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues</hi> and large <hi>Preſents,</hi> which Monſieur <hi>De Rebenack</hi> ſcatter'd about in that Court; of which the <hi>Agent</hi> himſelf was ſo unwary, or ſo fooliſh, as to make his boaſts.</p>
            <p>The Elector of <hi>Saxony</hi> better underſtood his own Intereſt, and therefore would not bite at the <hi>Golden Hook,</hi> as one that diſdain'd the treacherous <hi>Offers</hi> of <hi>France;</hi> but the <hi>French</hi> King endeavour'd by other ways to raiſe him diſturbances in his own <hi>Family,</hi> and to ſet him at Variance with his <hi>Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,</hi> which would have ſtrangely imbroild him, had not the Emperor in time provided againſt thoſe <hi>Miſchiefs.</hi> However, leſt it ſhould be ſaid there was any <hi>Court</hi> in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>French</hi> King had not ſome <hi>Plough</hi> or other going, he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bears not to ſend into <hi>Saxony</hi> ſuch as know how to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate themſelves to the <hi>Humour</hi> of the <hi>Country,</hi> more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:43542:29"/> the ſtouteſt <hi>Drinkers</hi> he can find out, who by that means, making themſelves familiar at the <hi>Tables</hi> of the <hi>Great Perſons,</hi> watch their opportunities in the highth of <hi>Jollity</hi> and <hi>Compotation</hi> to draw the <hi>Worms</hi> out of their <hi>Noſes,</hi> and dive into the bottoms of their open'd hearts.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Palatine</hi> Electors, neither Father nor Son, would cloſe with the Intereſt of the <hi>French,</hi> and therefore his moſt <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> Majeſty ſacrificed the depopulated Cities of that Country to his <hi>Fury,</hi> even to the compaſſion of ſome that were the Executioners of his <hi>Rage;</hi> a Depopulation which none but ſuch Monſters of Men as the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King employs would have undertaken; Men ſo impious and fearleſs of God, that one of them being mildly reprehended for the <hi>burning</hi> of a fair <hi>Town,</hi> reply'd, <hi>That he would burn God in Heaven, if his Maſter the King of</hi> France <hi>commanded him to doe it.</hi> But per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King is of the Opinion of the <hi>Antient Galls,</hi> believing there is no way to give peace to a Country, but by rooting out the Inhabitants, according to that of <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus, Galli, ubi ſolitudinem fecerunt, pacem appellant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor could the Biſhop of <hi>Munſter,</hi> as cunning as he was, preſerve himſelf from being out-witted by the <hi>French</hi> infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. For that being comprehended in the League of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> when he found himſelf attack'd by the States of <hi>Holland</hi> within the Empire, he implored the Aid of <hi>France</hi> according to the <hi>Guarranty,</hi> but in vain; for which when he was about to make his complaint, he was of a ſudden overwhelm'd with the Forces of <hi>France,</hi> and had not his Enemies us'd Moderation to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward him more than his own <hi>Allie,</hi> his Territories though the <hi>Patrimony</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> had been laid in Aſhes before now.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>French</hi> King broke Faith with <hi>Holland,</hi> to the ſurprize of a great part of their <hi>Country,</hi> he was ſo far from aſſigning any <hi>Cauſe, true</hi> or <hi>falſe,</hi> for his Actions, that he on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly publiſh'd a <hi>Declaration</hi> of <hi>War</hi> without any other <hi>Reaſons,</hi> than only the <hi>Ill ſatisfaction which His Majeſty had of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour of the States General toward him, being riſen to that Degree, that he can no longer without Diminution of his Glory, diſſemble his Indignation againſt them,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Therefore he had
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:43542:30"/> reſolv'd to make War againſt them by Sea and Land,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And commands all his Subjects</hi> courir ſus <hi>upon the</hi> Hollanders, <hi>for ſuch is Our Pleaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Certainly it was never known that in any Age or Nation in the World the Sword was drawn upon no better Allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; a ſtyle ſo far from being Moſt <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> that nothing but ſome <hi>French Romance</hi> could parallel the Expreſſion. All that can be ſaid, 'twas <hi>A-la-mode de France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Holland</hi> had no reaſon to wonder at theſe proceedings, conſidering what a <hi>Prank</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King had plaid them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when he pretended to joyn with them in the War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>England.</hi> At what time <hi>France,</hi> by virtue of a Treaty of <hi>Guarranty</hi> with the States of the United Provinces, after ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral requeſts ineffectally made by the States, found her ſelf oblig'd to make a ſhew of undertaking to defend them againſt <hi>England;</hi> among the reſt of the <hi>Articles,</hi> there was one by which it was concluded and agreed in expreſs terms, that the <hi>Allies</hi> ſhould not <hi>Negotiate,</hi> much leſs conclude any Peace or Truce with the common Enemy, without the conſent of the other, and without procuring the ſame ſatisfaction for his <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie,</hi> as he would for himſelf. The States tied themſelves with that <hi>Integrity</hi> to this Obligation, that notwithſtanding the conſiderable Advantages offer'd them to treat ſeparately; they would not ſo much as lend an Ear to any Propoſition of that <hi>Nature. France</hi> on the other ſide, had always kept on <hi>Foot</hi> a private <hi>Negotiation,</hi> which nevertheleſs the <hi>Dutch</hi> had all the <hi>Reaſon</hi> in the <hi>World</hi> to ſuſpect, becauſe of the continual Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Curriers</hi> between <hi>Paris</hi> and <hi>London.</hi> However <hi>France</hi> confirm'd them ſo authentickly in a contrary belief, and gave them ſuch poſitive Promiſes, that ſhe would never hearken to any Propoſition, unleſs in a joint Aſſembly, for a <hi>General Peace,</hi> that ſhe order'd the Count <hi>D' Eſtrades,</hi> that in Caſe the <hi>States</hi> would not give <hi>Credit</hi> to what he aſſured them as an <hi>Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour,</hi> he ſhould quit that <hi>Character</hi> for ſo long time, and pawn his Faith to them as a Private Perſon. A great honour indeed to the <hi>Count d' Eſtrade,</hi> to have the Reputation of a Perſon that would not tell an untruth, but under the <hi>Character</hi> of a
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:43542:30"/> Publick <hi>Miniſter</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and that the <hi>Probity</hi> of his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon was above the <hi>Dignity</hi> of his <hi>Employment.</hi> Though had he been ſo improvident to have been bound for his Maſter, he muſt certainly have anſwered both the <hi>Principal</hi> and <hi>Intereſt;</hi> for certain it is that <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France</hi> concluded the Peace without the <hi>conſent</hi> or ſo much as the <hi>knowledge</hi> of the <hi>States;</hi> neither did <hi>France</hi> make any mention of them or their Intereſts, or of any reſerve or relation to the <hi>General Peace.</hi> But that which was more <hi>ſurprizing</hi> was this, that after the <hi>French</hi> King had thus concluded a <hi>private Peace</hi> with <hi>England,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he had promis'd the King not to exerciſe any <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Hoſtility</hi> againſt him, he us'd all his endeavours to oblige the <hi>Dutch</hi> to put forth their <hi>Fleet</hi> to <hi>Sea, engaging</hi> to join with them, and <hi>agreeing</hi> upon all the <hi>Conditions</hi> neceſſary for that purpoſe. A double headed piece of <hi>Treachery,</hi> fit to be recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the <hi>Eternal Infamy</hi> of the <hi>Faith Breaker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we look into <hi>Sweden,</hi> we ſhall find that ſhe was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd as more potent than <hi>Denmark,</hi> and therefore a <hi>League</hi> was clapt up with them, to prevent the <hi>Danes</hi> aſſiſting <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and by that <hi>League</hi> the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> was to receive by way of <hi>Penſion</hi> or <hi>Gratuity,</hi> Sixteen Hundred Thouſand <hi>Crowns.</hi> But the <hi>French,</hi> upon ſecond <hi>Thoughts,</hi> finding the <hi>Treaty</hi> with the <hi>Sweeds</hi> to be of little uſe to them, refus'd to ratifie it, and ſent away <hi>Monſieur Trelon,</hi> to tell the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> in ſhort, that his Maſter declard it void; a quick and <hi>Majeſtick</hi> way to reſcind a <hi>Treaty</hi> at any time.</p>
            <p>If we remove into <hi>Poland,</hi> there you ſhall find no body more <hi>buſie</hi> than the <hi>French</hi> King's <hi>Ambaſſadors</hi> at the <hi>Elections</hi> of the King, to procure the choice of ſuch a one as may be tack'd to his <hi>Intereſt,</hi> or at leaſt ſuch a one as may have no kindneſs to the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and all this to enable him the more to diſturb the Peace of the <hi>Empire.</hi> In purſuance of which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly deſigns, under a pretence of Advancing the <hi>Affairs</hi> of <hi>Poland,</hi> and ſettling a perfect <hi>Amity</hi> with that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King contriv'd a <hi>Marriage</hi> for the <hi>Poliſh Prince,</hi> with a <hi>Lady</hi> of <hi>France.</hi> By which means he had a fair opportunity to ſend thither as her <hi>Attendents,</hi> and for the more <hi>Splendor</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:43542:31"/> of her <hi>Fame,</hi> ſo many expert <hi>Inſtruments</hi> of <hi>Miſchief,</hi> that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately they form'd and ſettl'd a <hi>Cabal</hi> with ſuch <hi>Intrigues</hi> as in a ſhort time <hi>enflam'd</hi> the <hi>Nobility</hi> of that <hi>Kingdom</hi> into <hi>Animoſities</hi> and <hi>Factions,</hi> not likely to be ſo ſoon again <hi>extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd:</hi> And at that time they wrought ſo far, that the King ſoon after became willing to reſign the <hi>Kingdom;</hi> upon which, the <hi>Turk,</hi> ſeeing the great <hi>Diviſions</hi> that were rais'd among them, was the more eaſily allur'd in by the <hi>French Cabal,</hi> who procur'd by <hi>Verſallian</hi>'s directions that <hi>Miſchief,</hi> partly out of <hi>revenge</hi> becauſe they could not compaſs another King either of <hi>French Bloud</hi> or <hi>French Intereſt</hi> at the next <hi>Election,</hi> and partly, becauſe the <hi>New King</hi> had contracted a <hi>Marriage</hi> with the <hi>Emperour</hi>'s Siſter.</p>
            <p>And now <hi>Poland,</hi> by reaſon of its <hi>Situation,</hi> being ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered under the <hi>Wings</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſador, is fix'd upon by the <hi>French,</hi> to convey themſelves from thence into <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary,</hi> and the <hi>Ottoman Port,</hi> for the better and more eaſie carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on their <hi>Intrigues</hi> between <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>Male Contents,</hi> and the <hi>Turk.</hi> And firſt, it appear'd by ſeveral <hi>Letters</hi> diſperſed both in <hi>Conſtantinople, Tranſilvania,</hi> and <hi>Hungary,</hi> that upon the <hi>30th.</hi> of <hi>December,</hi> 1681. the War was reſolv'd upon, and Sworn to againſt the Emperor, in the <hi>Serraglio</hi> of <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> in the <hi>Holy Council,</hi> call'd the <hi>Divan,</hi> where the <hi>Mufti, High Prieſt</hi> of the <hi>Mahomitan</hi> Religion, ſits Preſident. Which ſufficiently laid open the Authors and Procurers of that War, and clearly ſhew'd, that the <hi>French</hi> were not aſham'd, as if it had been a famous <hi>Action</hi> in them to take advice of the <hi>Divan,</hi> and applaud the ſucceſs of the <hi>Negotiation,</hi> as they did in their <hi>Letters</hi> written backwards and forwards to the <hi>Rebels,</hi> in which they congratulated with the <hi>Rebels;</hi> for having drawn the <hi>Rebels</hi> to their Succour, they promis'd each other in their <hi>Letters</hi> all the <hi>Advantages</hi> they could expect, which aim'd at no leſs than to have driven the Emperor out of the beſt of his <hi>Dominions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was known that ſuch of the <hi>Hungarians</hi> as were forc'd to run their <hi>Country</hi> for conſpiring againſt the Emperor, liv'd on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon ſuch ſupplies of Money as they receiv'd from the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:43542:31"/> 
               <hi>French,</hi> to the end they ſhould not be conſtrain'd to make their <hi>Peace</hi> with the <hi>Emperour,</hi> whoſe <hi>Clemency</hi> they were made believe extended no farther than to offer it; ſo that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to proſecute their Enterprize upon the Promiſes that were made them from <hi>France.</hi> Which was the reaſon that <hi>Akakia</hi> renewed and confirm'd more powerfully than ever the <hi>League</hi> and <hi>Alliance</hi> with the <hi>Male-Contents</hi> in <hi>Hungary.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> Emiſſaries alſo, without any ſhame of violating the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nations,</hi> and in <hi>Countries</hi> where the Solemn <hi>Treaty</hi> of <hi>Peace</hi> was in full force, though they had been manifeſtly diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in a ſecret <hi>Conſpiracy,</hi> run on afterwards more than ever with an unparallell'd <hi>Impudence,</hi> as if all things had been law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for them to act without controul.</p>
            <p>An Hunderd Thouſand <hi>Florins</hi> were ordered at <hi>Paris</hi> to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the <hi>Diſcontents</hi> of the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Rebels, and quicken the Motion of the <hi>Turks;</hi> which ſumm was deliver'd at <hi>Dant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zick,</hi> and paid into the Hands of a <hi>Banker,</hi> who afterwards deliver'd it into the Hands of the <hi>French Emiſſaries,</hi> at ſeveral Payments, the better to hide the Buſineſs. And the <hi>Sieur du Vernay Boucauldi, Count Teckely</hi>'s real Spie, caus'd to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd to the <hi>Sieur Valentine Nemeſſan 11300 Duckats,</hi> to oblige the <hi>Male-Contents</hi> to take <hi>Arms</hi> again<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and attack the Citta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del of <hi>Zatmar,</hi> after the <hi>French</hi> Mode; that is, to endeavour to gain the <hi>Garriſon</hi> or <hi>Citizens</hi> with Money.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Tricks</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> Emiſſaries were ſo well known, that the Princeſs <hi>Radzivilliana</hi> forbad the ſuffering any <hi>French</hi> to paſs through her Countrey of <hi>Saculia,</hi> fearing leſt they ſhould as in other Places, corrupt her People with Money, and one being taken paſſing through her <hi>Countrey,</hi> was by her command laden with <hi>Irons,</hi> and ſeverely <hi>puniſh'd.</hi> Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they took other <hi>Roads,</hi> and had frequent private enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>views with <hi>Valentin Nemeſſan, Peter Jagel,</hi> and other parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Friends and Allies of <hi>Teckely.</hi> They made it their Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs likewiſe to have more and more frequent conferences in <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> ſending firſt one, and then another to <hi>Paris</hi> with ample Accounts of their Proceedings, and for farther In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:43542:32"/>
            <p>Of all theſe things the Emperours Ambaſſador in the Court of <hi>Poland</hi> complain'd to his Majeſty, and deſir'd that no <hi>French</hi> Man, not being an Ambaſſador, or bearing ſome other Employment, might be permitted to ſtay in his <hi>Dominions.</hi> Upon which the King gave Notice to the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſador, to order <hi>Akakia</hi> and <hi>Du Vernay</hi> to withdraw: The <hi>Senate</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo told the ſame Ambaſſador, that they well underſtood that the <hi>French</hi> were they who had ſtirr'd up the <hi>Troubles</hi> in <hi>Hungary;</hi> that they knew what <hi>Money</hi> had been given for it, what <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals</hi> they had held, and what the <hi>Sieur du Vernay</hi> kept <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>very day. They declared him to be a <hi>Spie,</hi> and that he had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther buſineſs to detain him about <hi>Leopold,</hi> but only to treat with the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Mahometans</hi> about drawing the <hi>War</hi> into <hi>Hungary.</hi> The Ambaſſador anſwered, that <hi>Vernay</hi> was ſent with him into <hi>Poland</hi> to manage the <hi>Affairs</hi> of the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King his <hi>Maſter,</hi> and deny'd that either <hi>Vernay</hi> or he had any commerce with the <hi>Hungarians</hi> or <hi>Turks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ambaſſador having made new <hi>Diſcoveries,</hi> renew'd his complaints to the King, who gave him <hi>Audience</hi> in the preſence of <hi>Vitry</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſador, and before the whole <hi>Senate;</hi> where he ſpoke a long time againſt the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable <hi>Methods</hi> and <hi>Practices</hi> of the <hi>French,</hi> carry'd on by <hi>Vernay,</hi> to promote the <hi>Troubles</hi> of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and bring the <hi>Turks</hi> into <hi>Chriſtendom;</hi> but then it was that <hi>Vitry,</hi> having no way to avoid it, declar'd <hi>Vernay</hi> to be joint Ambaſſador with him from the <hi>French</hi> King<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by that means to ſhelter a <hi>Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> to <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> under the Protection of the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Much about the ſame time the <hi>Caſtellan</hi> of <hi>Primiſlau</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that neither His Majeſty of <hi>Poland</hi> nor the <hi>Senate</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll'd the <hi>French</hi> Spies, and moreover that their deſigns ſtill ſucceeded better and better, refus'd to permit <hi>Vernay</hi> to enter his <hi>Village</hi> of <hi>Nimoravia,</hi> but forced him to paſs another way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vitry</hi> was highly incens'd at this, and going directly to Court, laid before the King the <hi>Affront</hi> and <hi>Indignity</hi> offer'd to his Aſſociate <hi>Vernay,</hi> and was ſo bold as to demand the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment</hi> of the <hi>Caſtellan</hi> for ſatisfaction; but the King not
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:43542:32"/> enduring his <hi>Confidence,</hi> told him plainly, that it was to no purpoſe to couch <hi>Vernay</hi> under the Quality of an Ambaſſador, for that the <hi>Tragedies</hi> he acted under the vain pretence of an Ambaſſador, were too well known; that all the <hi>devices</hi> of the <hi>French,</hi> and their <hi>contracts</hi> with the <hi>Turk</hi> were diſcover'd, that the places which <hi>Vernay</hi> had corrupted were named; their <hi>Reſolutions</hi> and <hi>Deſigns</hi> known, that he could exactly tell how much Money had been remitted from <hi>France</hi> to <hi>Hungary,</hi> and how they had us'd <hi>Violence, Deceit,</hi> and wicked <hi>Practice</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Emperour, to the misfortune of <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Ambaſſador would have pretended to have clear'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of theſe things, which he ſaid were <hi>wrongfully</hi> charg'd upon his Nation. But the King growing <hi>hot,</hi> would not hear him, only told the Ambaſſador he would lay Ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand <hi>Piſtoles</hi> with him, that he would <hi>undeniably</hi> prove all that he had ſaid to be true.</p>
            <p>At which the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſador ſtood amaz'd, and by his ſilence ſufficiently <hi>confirm'd</hi> the thing. The reſt of the <hi>French</hi> that were preſent alſo, in a <hi>Conſternation</hi> fix'd their <hi>Eyes</hi> upon the <hi>Ground;</hi> not lifting them up, but to gaze upon one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as it were <hi>accuſing</hi> themſelves. So certain it is, that the inward reproach of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and the ſecret <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> put the moſt fierce and confident out of <hi>Countenance,</hi> and by reducing the <hi>Guilty</hi> to a ſhamefull <hi>Silence,</hi> force them to make ſome ſort of confeſſion of their <hi>Crimes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides what has been recited, there were ſeveral <hi>Letters</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercepted, which clear'd up the <hi>Truth</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Hungarian</hi> Male-Contents. One from Monſieur <hi>Vernay</hi> to <hi>Count Teckely,</hi> wherein the <hi>French</hi> Spie tells him, that he had receiv'd with great joy the <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> which he ſent him from the <hi>Camp</hi> before <hi>Filleck,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clos'd in the Packets of the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſador at <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople.</hi> That he had endeavour'd to ſend <hi>Jaygell</hi> what he had promis'd him, and what he had receiv'd, but wanted an Opportunity; farther he deſir'd the <hi>Count</hi> to order it ſo, that his <hi>Meſſengers</hi> ſhould come to him by <hi>Night,</hi> and directed him which Road they ſhould take, to avoid the Searches of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:43542:33"/> the <hi>Polonians,</hi> concluding that he ſhould take care in all things that the Count ſhould be pleas'd to command him.</p>
            <p>Another <hi>Letter</hi> from Count <hi>Teckely</hi> to <hi>Vernay,</hi> wherein the Count gives <hi>Vernay</hi> thanks to his faithfull Agent <hi>Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Nemeſſani,</hi> and promiſes him to acknowledge it, as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion ſhould ſerve; gives him an account of his taking <hi>Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſovia</hi> and <hi>Filleck,</hi> and how he intended to proſecute his good Succeſs.</p>
            <p>Another <hi>Letter</hi> from <hi>Peter Jaygell</hi> Governour of <hi>Caſſovia</hi> to Monſieur <hi>Vernay;</hi> wherein <hi>Jaygell</hi> gives <hi>Vernay</hi> an Account of the taking and diſmantling of <hi>Filleck,</hi> that <hi>Teckely</hi> had been Proclaim'd King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and confirm'd in that Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity by the Great <hi>Turk,</hi> who ſent him from the Port a <hi>Hat</hi> inſtead of a <hi>Crown,</hi> a <hi>Standard,</hi> and a <hi>Sceptre.</hi> He tells <hi>Vernay</hi> farther, that <hi>Nemeſſani</hi> was gone to treat of <hi>Affairs</hi> at the <hi>French</hi> King's Court, and preſſes <hi>Vernay</hi> to haſten the ſupply promis'd by the <hi>French</hi> King.</p>
            <p>Sufficient Proofs of the pernicious and Moſt <hi>Anti-Chriſtian</hi> Treacheries of the Moſt <hi>Christian</hi> King to the ruin of <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi> After all this, to ſhew the extent of <hi>French</hi> falſhood, you ſhall ſee that if it ſtand with his own Intereſt, the <hi>French</hi> King will not ſtick to betray himſelf, and diſcover his own <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons;</hi> for that at the beginning of the <hi>Dutch</hi> War, when he ſaw the Emperour arming himſelf in good earneſt to aſſiſt the <hi>Dutch,</hi> to diſſuade and divert him from his purpoſe; and to engage him, had it been poſſible, not to concern himſelf in the <hi>Quarrel,</hi> he very fairly offer'd to deliver into the Emperour's hands all the Original <hi>Letters</hi> and <hi>Papers</hi> he had receiv'd from time to time from his <hi>brib'd Friends</hi> and Creatures in <hi>Poland</hi> and <hi>Hungary,</hi> to the end that both his <hi>Imperial Majesty</hi> and the King of <hi>Poland</hi> might take ſuch Orders as they thought fit with thoſe <hi>Traitors<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> may ſerve as a fare warning and determent to all thoſe that prefer <hi>French</hi> Money before their Loyalty, and the true Intereſts of their Country.</p>
            <p>'Tis true that for ſome time the Moſt <hi>Christian</hi> King made the raiſing of his Seige from before <hi>Luxenburgh</hi> a great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of his <hi>Christian.</hi> Zeal and Generoſity to his Imperial
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:43542:33"/> Majeſty, not to aſſail him when the <hi>Turk</hi> was at his Doors, but the true ground of his retiring, was this notwithſtanding his ſpecious pretences, at the inſtance of the Confederates, all good Offices were done by the King of <hi>England,</hi> and Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials given, but all to no effect, till the word <hi>Parliament</hi> was put into them. That powerfull word had ſuch a <hi>charm</hi> in it, that even at a diſtance it raiſed the <hi>Siege;</hi> which may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince us of what <hi>Efficacy</hi> a King of <hi>England</hi>'s words are when he will give them their full weight, and threaten with his <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then it is that he appears that greater <hi>Figure</hi> which we ought to repreſent him in our <hi>Minds,</hi> the Nation his <hi>Body,</hi> he the <hi>Head,</hi> and join'd with that <hi>Harmony</hi> that every word he pronounces is the Word of a <hi>Kingdom.</hi> Such Words are as effectual as <hi>Fleets</hi> and <hi>Armies,</hi> becauſe they can create them; and without this, his Word ſounds abroad like a <hi>Faint Whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> that is either not heard, or which is worſe, not min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p>But to return to the <hi>French</hi> King, and bring him home to his own <hi>Dominions,</hi> where you ſhall find his extraordinary <hi>Kindneſs</hi> to his then Highneſs the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> in <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſhing</hi> the <hi>Castle,</hi> and pulling down the <hi>Walls</hi> of the chief <hi>City</hi> of his <hi>Principality</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> to ſave him the expence of a <hi>Garriſon,</hi> and <hi>Plundering</hi> and <hi>Exacting</hi> vaſt Summs of Money from the <hi>Subjects</hi> of another <hi>Prince,</hi> living in Peace and giving him no Diſturbance, merely under pretence of entertaining the Children of <hi>Hugonots.</hi> Nay, you ſhall find him perſecuting his own <hi>Subjects</hi> under the Name of <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> and ſending his Miſſionary <hi>Dragoons</hi> to conver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them by ranſacking their <hi>Houſes,</hi> robbing them of their <hi>Goods,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filing their <hi>Wives,</hi> deflowring their <hi>Daughters,</hi> and inflicting upon the <hi>Men</hi> torments more <hi>cruel</hi> and <hi>inhumane</hi> than thoſe of the <hi>Ten Perſecutions;</hi> and all this while, they were under the <hi>Protection</hi> of ſeveral Edicts, ſolemnly granted and ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them for the Exerciſe of their Religion without diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:43542:34"/>
            <p>Theſe are the Renowned Acts of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. diſplaying the lovely proſpect of his <hi>Falſhood</hi> to <hi>England,</hi> his breach of <hi>Faith</hi> with <hi>Spain,</hi> his <hi>Infidelity</hi> to <hi>Holland,</hi> his <hi>Juggling</hi> with the <hi>Northern</hi> Princes, his <hi>Treacherous Aſpiring</hi> to the <hi>Imperial Throne,</hi> his vaſt <hi>Expences</hi> to divide the Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> from the <hi>Empire,</hi> his <hi>endangering</hi> the <hi>ſubverſion</hi> of all <hi>Christendom</hi> by confederating with the <hi>Turk,</hi> and his <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olations</hi> of the <hi>Peace</hi> of his own <hi>Subjects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, it has been his common <hi>Practice</hi> to give the World all manner of <hi>Diſturbance,</hi> and to render <hi>France</hi> the common <hi>Enemy</hi> of the <hi>Peace</hi> of Manking, and a publick <hi>Peſt</hi> among all States and Princes; in every Countrey and Kingdom he either finds <hi>Combuſtible Stuff,</hi> or elſe makes it, and then ſets <hi>Fire</hi> to it, being at an exceſſive charge to find <hi>Fod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> for the various Animals of <hi>Faction</hi> in all <hi>Places.</hi> Which ſort of <hi>Politicks</hi> appear to be ſo much the more <hi>Criminal,</hi> becauſe there is no juſt revenging them, but that which obliges all generous <hi>Nations</hi> to fight their <hi>Enemies</hi> with their <hi>Arms</hi> in their hands, and openly. There being nothing ſo baſe as that which makes Men make uſe of wicked <hi>devices</hi> and execrable <hi>Treaſons</hi> as the inſtruments to ruine others; nor does he that thinks to aſſume the Name of <hi>Great</hi> by unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Artifices, render himſelf a whit the more truly <hi>Glorious:</hi> Souls truly Royal and Magnanimous have always deſpis'd the Conqueſts they could more eaſily obtain by <hi>Cunning</hi> and <hi>Trapan,</hi> than by <hi>Force</hi> and <hi>Arms:</hi> And it was out of their Opinion, worthy a Noble Spirit, that <hi>Alexander</hi> the great ſharply rebuk'd his Favourite <hi>Parmenio,</hi> who would have put him upon a crafty contrivance, telling him, it was only fit for <hi>Robbers</hi> to have recourſe to <hi>Treachery,</hi> as their only meanes to compaſs their <hi>Theiveries.</hi> But the <hi>French</hi> King is of another <hi>Temper,</hi> and thinks it more ſafe to conquer by <hi>Divide &amp; Impera,</hi> than by dint of <hi>Sword.</hi> He knows him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf good at <hi>Burning,</hi> witneſs <hi>Alſatia</hi> and the <hi>Palatinate</hi> laid in <hi>Aſhes,</hi> and therefore thinks it better to ſet other <hi>Countries,</hi> which he cannot otherwiſe come at, in a Flame by <hi>Treachery</hi> and <hi>Faction,</hi> that having enough to doe to quench their own
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:43542:34"/> Fires at home, they may have neither <hi>Leiſure</hi> nor <hi>Power</hi> to hinder his <hi>Projects</hi> abroad.</p>
            <p>Doubtleſs then, ſince <hi>England</hi> has ſo lately ſeen her <hi>Nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours Houſes</hi> in ſo ſad a conflagration, it is a ſufficient Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation for her to look to her own, and to ſecure her ſelf and all <hi>Europe</hi> from ſuch <hi>Boutefeus,</hi> and the ſaid effects of their impious deſigns.</p>
            <p>Seeing then there is ſo little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>redit to be given to the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaginian</hi> Faith of <hi>France,</hi> and that all the <hi>Motions</hi> of that aſpiring <hi>Monarch</hi> tend directly to the ſubverſion of the whole frame of the <hi>Government</hi> of <hi>Europe,</hi> and to erect a <hi>French Tyranny</hi> over all the enthrall'd <hi>Princes</hi> of this ſame fourth and beſt inhabited part of the World, there are two <hi>Motives</hi> which ought to excite the <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> to take the common cauſe in <hi>hand:</hi> the one is intereſt of <hi>State,</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſtrickt obligation of <hi>Juſtice.</hi> The firſt is, the general concern of all the <hi>Potentates</hi> of <hi>Europe;</hi> the ſecond, the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular intereſt of the <hi>Princes</hi> of the <hi>Empire.</hi> We ſhall only take notice of the former, as being the moſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal,</hi> and moſt conſiderable in the World, and which will lead us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibly into the ſecond. The grand concern is now to ſupport the <hi>Right</hi> of <hi>Nations,</hi> which is common to all, and to prevent the introducing of <hi>Maxims</hi> into the World which deſtroy all commerce among Men, and will certainly render humane <hi>Society</hi> no leſs dangerous and inſupportable than that of <hi>Lions</hi> and <hi>Tygers;</hi> to defend the publick Faith of <hi>Treaties,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move from the ſight of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> a ſcandalous example, which, by the fatal <hi>conſequences</hi> of it, will ſurrender the <hi>moſt feeble</hi> to the <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Pleaſure</hi> of the ſtrongeſt and moſt <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent;</hi> to ſtop the <hi>Inundation</hi> of a <hi>Rapid Torrent,</hi> againſt the impetuoſity of which neither <hi>Leagues</hi> nor <hi>Marriages,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Oaths</hi> nor <hi>Ties</hi> of <hi>Bloud</hi> and <hi>Parentage,</hi> neither <hi>Amity</hi> nor <hi>Condeſcentions,</hi> are <hi>Mounds</hi> or <hi>Damms</hi> ſufficient to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the common <hi>Bulwark</hi> of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> againſt a vaſt <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign,</hi> which has no other ground than the Inſatiable thirſt of <hi>Conquest,</hi> no other end than deſpotick <hi>Domination</hi> by dint of <hi>Arms,</hi> and ſlight of <hi>Intrigue,</hi> nor any <hi>Limits</hi> but ſuch as
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:43542:35"/> 
               <hi>Fortune</hi> ſhall preſcribe. In ſhort, <hi>England</hi> is now to decide the <hi>Fate</hi> of <hi>Europe,</hi> and to pronounce the Sentence of her <hi>Liberty</hi> or <hi>Bondage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor does there want juſtification ſufficient to purſue ſo great and glorious an Undertaking to the utmoſt, when we conſider the <hi>Maxims</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> which are eaſie to be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd from the paſt and preſent conduct, her inſulting <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch;</hi> whoſe deſign was to have thrown his <hi>Waſh-pot</hi> over the <hi>Empire,</hi> and his <hi>Shoe</hi> over all the reſt of <hi>Europe.</hi> The firſt <hi>Mixim</hi> of <hi>France</hi> is, to make War alwaies abroad, and to exerciſe her <hi>Young Nobility</hi> at the expence of her <hi>Nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</hi> A <hi>Maxim</hi> very <hi>Politick,</hi> and well adjuſted for her own <hi>Advantage;</hi> but very incommodious for all the reſt of the <hi>World:</hi> For it is certain the <hi>Genius</hi> of that <hi>Nation</hi> cannot long endure the <hi>Calms</hi> of a <hi>Lazy Peace,</hi> ſo that if you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find employment for them abroad, they will be framing <hi>Commotions</hi> and <hi>Diſturbances</hi> at home. The Eldeſt Sons of all their <hi>Noble Families</hi> carry away the <hi>Eſtates</hi> without lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any thing to the <hi>Younger,</hi> but an empty <hi>Title</hi> and their <hi>Swords;</hi> ſo that being little addicted to <hi>Learning,</hi> and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining the life of <hi>Mechanicks,</hi> nothing remains but <hi>War,</hi> or <hi>Thievery,</hi> to reſcue them from <hi>Miſery;</hi> which is the reaſon that the <hi>Politicks</hi> of <hi>France</hi> oblige her to be continually picking Quarrels with her <hi>Nighbours,</hi> to evaporate thoſe <hi>Flames,</hi> which otherwiſe would <hi>prey</hi> upon her own <hi>Bowels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their ſecond <hi>Maxim</hi> is, to <hi>inſinuate</hi> themſelves into all ſorts of <hi>Affairs</hi> on which hand ſoever it be, and to make themſelves <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mpires</hi> in all <hi>buſineſs,</hi> either by <hi>Force</hi> or <hi>Subtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> by <hi>Threatnings,</hi> or under pretence of <hi>Friendſhip,</hi> to wrig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle themſelves into <hi>Treaties</hi> of <hi>Peace</hi> where they are Parties intereſted, as they did in that of the Biſhop of <hi>Munſter,</hi> and afterwards in the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> at <hi>Breda.</hi> There never was any Quarrel wherein they had not the <hi>cunning</hi> to pretend ſome <hi>Intereſt</hi> or <hi>Right;</hi> and never any People ſhew'd the leaſt inclination to rebell, but they always made them their <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies.</hi> But experience tells us that they never took part in any <hi>War</hi> but to enflame it the more, nor ever interpos'd
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:43542:35"/> in any Peace, to Sow the Seeds of new Differences.</p>
            <p>Their third <hi>Maxim</hi> is to make <hi>Intereſt of State</hi> the only rule of all their Actions, without having any regard to the <hi>Faith</hi> of <hi>Treaties,</hi> or the <hi>Sanctity</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> or any other Ties of <hi>Parentage</hi> or <hi>Friendſhip,</hi> according to the Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Principle of the D. of <hi>Rohan, That Princes commanded the People, and Intereſt, commanded Princes:</hi> So that all that the <hi>Turks</hi> have gain'd upon <hi>Europe</hi> from the time of <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt till this time, they owe to their Alliances with <hi>France,</hi> and the Diverſions ſhe had made in their favour, by giving diſturbance to thoſe that enterpriz'd any thing againſt the common Enemy.</p>
            <p>Their fourth <hi>Maxim</hi> is, to keep, as much as in them lies, all Foreign States employ'd and divided at home, or elſe engaged in <hi>Foreign War,</hi> (of which <hi>England</hi> in particular has found the ſad <hi>Effects,</hi>) and under pretence of aſſiſting ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times one, ſometimes another, to ſeek their own <hi>Advantages</hi> in the <hi>Troubles</hi> of others.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the <hi>Maxims</hi> of Men that make haſte to be <hi>Rich</hi> in <hi>Ignoble Conqueſts;</hi> and the infallible marks of a profound and vaſt deſign, that muſt be ſtopp'd in time, to ſtop the ſpreading of the <hi>Ambitious Grangrene;</hi> for from a <hi>Royal</hi> and powerfull <hi>Profeſſor</hi> of ſuch <hi>Maxims</hi> as theſe, there is no <hi>Prince</hi> that can be ſafe in his <hi>Dominions.</hi> Among private Perſons it is the moſt difficult thing to deal with a Man of a large Conſcience; how much more a moſt <hi>Herculean</hi> task it is to cope with a mighty <hi>Potentate</hi> whoſe Conſcience is no leſs wide than his <hi>Ambition</hi> is <hi>Vaſt,</hi> who having eleven Millions of Sterling Pounds, torn from the <hi>Bowels</hi> and <hi>Mouths</hi> of his poor and wanting <hi>Subjects,</hi> at command to maintain his Wars, and bribe his way to Conqueſt through all the Fences of <hi>Religion, Morality,</hi> and <hi>Common Juſtice,</hi> values not the tremendous Anger of <hi>Heaven,</hi> nor the Violation of all the Laws of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi> nor the preſervative Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of Men to attain his ends. It is ſaid of <hi>Tamerlane,</hi> though a <hi>Scythian</hi> and <hi>Barbarian,</hi> that to one who earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly importun'd him in behalf of <hi>Bajazet,</hi> he made this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:43542:36"/> that he did not puniſh a <hi>King</hi> but an <hi>impions</hi> and <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>farious</hi> Man. The ſame juſtification have the Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> that they fight not againſt the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King, but an Anti-Chriſtian <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper,</hi> who <hi>conquers</hi> to <hi>oppreſs,</hi> and <hi>oppreſſes</hi> merely to <hi>ſupport</hi> his <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> and ſhew the <hi>Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur</hi> of his <hi>Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>England</hi> has more juſt pretences to his <hi>Dominions,</hi> than perhaps he has himſelf, at leaſt far more juſt than what he has to the conqueſts which he has wreſted out of the hands of the <hi>Spaniard</hi> and the <hi>Emperor. England</hi> has the greateſt Reaſon in the World to recover her Antient, and till lately unconteſted <hi>Glory,</hi> and aſſert her long continued <hi>Dominions</hi> of the <hi>Seas,</hi> uſurp'd by the Aſſiſtence of a purchas'd <hi>Navy,</hi> which if once <hi>deſtroy'd,</hi> nothing but the ſame opportunities could again <hi>recover.</hi> It is ſaid that the <hi>Portcullis</hi> was added to the <hi>Royal Badges</hi> of the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> to ſignifie that the Kings of <hi>England</hi> had a juſt <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Title,</hi> at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to ſhut up and open the <hi>Sea</hi> when they thought fit; and it may ſtill be prov'd by ſeveral ſubſtantial Evidences, that the King of <hi>England</hi>'s Title to the Propriety of the <hi>Sea,</hi> is as good and perhaps better than any Title the <hi>French</hi> King has to any part of his <hi>Dominions</hi> by <hi>Land.</hi> And the Letters are ſtill to be ſeen in the <hi>Paper-Office</hi> at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> if not remov'd, Written by this King's Grandfather with his own hand to King <hi>James,</hi> to ask leave for ſome few <hi>Veſſels</hi> to Fiſh for <hi>Sowles,</hi> as he ſhould have occaſion for his own Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and it ought to be ſo agen, for it is only fit that <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſhould guard the Seas, that ſo well defend and guard Her. Juſtice it ſelf now loudly calls to <hi>England</hi> to demand ſatisfaction for the illegal and vexatious Depredations and Practices committed upon her Merchants, even at the time when ſhe was in ſtricteſt <hi>League</hi> and <hi>Combination</hi> with her, to the ruine of her Trade, which is the <hi>Apple</hi> of her <hi>Eye,</hi> and the main ſupport of her <hi>Wooden Walls,</hi> her chiefeſt <hi>Glory,</hi> and, next under <hi>Heaven,</hi> her chiefeſt <hi>Safeguard</hi> and <hi>Protection.</hi> She ought in <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> to reſent the Indignities and Affronts ſo lately put upon her, in making her that ought
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:43542:36"/> to be the <hi>Balance</hi> of <hi>Europe,</hi> the <hi>Deriſion</hi> of her <hi>Enemies,</hi> and only the Pity of her Friends; ſuch a generous Animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity and Reſentment as this would wean the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation from that fond <hi>Dotage</hi> upon <hi>French</hi> Baubles, <hi>French</hi> Faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and <hi>French</hi> Vermin, to the loſs of above Sixteen Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Thouſand Pounds Yearly to this Kingdom, (there ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been Yearly ſo much more imported of <hi>French</hi> Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, than exported of ours,) which only ſerves to enrich the <hi>Capital Foe</hi> to our own <hi>Ruine,</hi> and to fit us for the <hi>Yoke</hi> of <hi>French</hi> Slavery. For this is a certain Rule, that the firſt ſtep to the ſubducing of a <hi>Nation</hi> is to inſinuate into them a good liking, or rather a <hi>dotage</hi> of thoſe that are to be their ſubduers; and therefore it was, that the <hi>French</hi> King obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, that while the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were under the <hi>Conjunction</hi> of the <hi>Triple League,</hi> there was a general humour in the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in oppoſition to <hi>Frence,</hi> inſomuch that they had thrown off the <hi>French Mode</hi> and put on <hi>Veſts,</hi> to the end we might look the more like a diſtinct People, and not be under the ſervility of <hi>Imitation,</hi> which alwaies pays a greater reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the <hi>Original,</hi> than is conſiſtent with that Equality which all independent <hi>Nations</hi> ſhould pretend to; I ſay the the <hi>French</hi> King obſerving this, did not like this ſmall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of ill <hi>Humours,</hi> wiſely conſidering it as a natural <hi>Introduction,</hi> firſt to make the World his <hi>Apes,</hi> and then his <hi>Slaves;</hi> and therefore he ſet his Inſtruments at work to <hi>Laugh</hi> us out of our <hi>Veſts,</hi> which ſhe performed ſo effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, that in a Moment, like ſo many <hi>Footmen</hi> who had quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their Maſters <hi>Livery,</hi> we all took it up again, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd to ſerve the <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And happy would it be for <hi>England</hi> if ſhe would caſt off her <hi>French</hi> Modes, her <hi>French</hi> Faſhions, and <hi>French</hi> Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, which only ſerve to corrupt and ſoften the minds of thoſe for whom it would be much more glorious to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Fields of <hi>Poictiers</hi> and <hi>Agencourt,</hi> and rather to ſtudy the generous Examples of their victorious Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, than be the Slaves of <hi>French</hi> Imitation. The conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Romans</hi> retir'd indeed to <hi>Athens</hi> to improve their Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning;
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:43542:37"/> but it betrays a poorneſs of Spirit inexcuſable in the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who have two ſuch Magnificent <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities</hi> of their own, to gallop to <hi>Paris</hi> for Breeding; as if <hi>Coupees, Complements, Grimaces,</hi> and <hi>Shrugs</hi> of the <hi>Shoulder</hi> were the only <hi>Accompliſhments</hi> of a <hi>Gentleman.</hi> Surely it was much better both for <hi>England</hi> and the General Peace of <hi>Europe,</hi> when the <hi>Engliſh</hi> taught them their running <hi>Sarrabands,</hi> and the good Breeding of Obedience, nor will it e'er be well, till the <hi>Engliſh</hi> become their <hi>Tutors</hi> again: For certainly there is no Government in <hi>Europe</hi> under which the People live ſo Miſerably, as under that of <hi>France;</hi> the Grand <hi>Signior,</hi> or the <hi>Kſar</hi> of <hi>Moſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vy</hi> are not more abſolute of the People than the <hi>Tyranny</hi> of <hi>France.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> King may well be call'd <hi>Tyrannus,</hi> for he makes and abrogates the Laws at his Pleaſure; he cannot be ſaid to <hi>Rule,</hi> but <hi>Tyrannize</hi> over <hi>Cities,</hi> depriv'd of all the <hi>Franchizes</hi> and <hi>Privileges</hi> that render <hi>Societies</hi> happy, and to dominier over a poor naked <hi>People,</hi> ſtript of all things that make life comfortable. So that the People may be ſaid to <hi>Toil</hi> and <hi>Moil,</hi> but the <hi>Prince</hi> to wipe off the Sweat of their <hi>Brows</hi> into his own <hi>Coffers.</hi> You would ſwear that the whole <hi>Country</hi> were the habitation of <hi>Poverty,</hi> where <hi>Penury</hi> walks about in wooden <hi>Sandals,</hi> ſingle <hi>Petti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oates,</hi> and wrinckl'd <hi>Faces,</hi> as if the Products of that fertile <hi>Soil</hi> were forbid to be touch'd by the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent <hi>Manurers</hi> of that Terreſtrial <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> where the <hi>Corn,</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> and Fat of the <hi>Land</hi> is carry'd off to fit the <hi>Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Magazines,</hi> or ſold abroad to cram the King's <hi>Exchequer.</hi> And after all this, when the ſholes of <hi>Locuſt Publicans</hi> have devour'd all, even almoſt to the very <hi>Stalk,</hi> for the ſmall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder to bear the Burthen of inſolent free <hi>Quarter,</hi> is not only <hi>Tyranny,</hi> but licentiated <hi>Inhumanity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All theſe <hi>Calamities</hi> and <hi>Miſeries</hi> has <hi>England</hi> yet eſcap'd, though fairly threaten'd with them, had not Providence been very mercifull to Her. The <hi>Husbandman</hi> plump and jolly, enjoying his Liberty and a fair proportion of his <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,</hi> does not fear what the Confuſion of <hi>Babel</hi> never knew the horrid <hi>Jargonry</hi> of</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:43542:37"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Ayde, Octroy, Preciput, Equivalent, Crue, Taille, Eſtate, Subſiſtence de quartier d'hyvere, Garinzons, Mort payes, Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments de Governours, Debtes &amp; Affaires du Roy, Gratifications Extraordinaries, Deu Gratuit, Frais.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The neceſſary ſupports of Life, Wine, Beer, Sider, are not enhanc'd by,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aydes ſur le Vin, Bierres &amp; Cidres, plus le Huictieme Denier, le Souqueſt, le Batire, Impoſts &amp; Billets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Markets are not peſter'd with <hi>Gabelles</hi> upon Corn and Meal, nor the Mills with <hi>Meaſure Coupee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No Tolls of <hi>pied Fourchue,</hi> nor <hi>Duties</hi> taken by weight upon every pound of <hi>Fleſh</hi> ſold in the <hi>Shambles,</hi> nor <hi>Gabelles</hi> upon <hi>Salt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> but what are laid on by conſent of the People themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Shop Keepers are not moleſted with the</hi> Gibbriſh <hi>of the mark upon Paper, the mark of Silver, the mark of Tinn, the mark of Hats, the mark of all Stockins, Silk, and Woollen, the mark of Shoes, the mark upon all Stuffs, Woollen, and Silk, the mark upon Linen, the Gabelle upon Jie, the controle of of Exploites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Gentry are not vex'd with the Tax of free Gifts, Fifts, and Reſiſts, and Amortiſements.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce of Valuation, the mark of Gold, the two Soulx in the Pound, the ſeal'd Duty, the duty of Controll, the regiſters Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the Prieſt for being admitted to the Annual, and the Annu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al or Paulette.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſort of Language of the <hi>Gallies,</hi> not underſtood by <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Liberty, yet all theſe and many other abominable Taxes, Tolls, and Impoſitions, are punctually leavy'd one way or other at the King's <hi>ſole Will</hi> and <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> with many more too prolix to be number'd, and what ever elſe his Abſolute Power ſhall think fit to impoſe anew, where ever any ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the <hi>French</hi> Monarchy have their habitations, when his emergent occaſions intimate a pretence, and muſt be paid without any remorce or compaſſion to the half Famiſh'd Children and Families of the poor People, crying out for <hi>Bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:43542:38"/>
            <p>Certainly to conclude therefore as I begun, the <hi>Lician Chimaera,</hi> and <hi>Lernaean Hydra</hi> that waſted all the Country round about them, and ruined the Inhabitants with the ſcal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Flames</hi> and Peſtilential <hi>Breath</hi> that iſſued from their Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferous <hi>Jaws,</hi> were Types of <hi>Tyranny</hi> in <hi>General,</hi> ſo more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly of the preſent <hi>French</hi> Monarchy; but on the other ſide, we find that both <hi>Bellerophon</hi> and <hi>Hercules</hi> continue to this day eterniz'd for ſubduing thoſe <hi>Monſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such Fables as theſe, being the Off-ſpring of great Reaſon, and wiſe Head peices, were not invented merely to pleaſe their <hi>Readers,</hi> but to inſtruct the <hi>World,</hi> that Wars, which unavoidably muſt be attended with great <hi>Miſchiefs</hi> and <hi>Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities,</hi> are not to be unjuſtly undertaken to doe wrong for wrong's ſake, under pretence of Illegal <hi>Claims</hi> and <hi>Pretenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> but may be legally enterpriz'd to repell <hi>injuſtice</hi> and <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> and to curb the lawleſs Invaſions of <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Property,</hi> which are the original <hi>Bleſſings</hi> and <hi>Benefits</hi> of God and Nature, the unjuſt <hi>Aſſailour</hi> of which becomes an Enemy to both; and a Monſter no leſs pernicious than either of thoſe two: For thoſe Monſters no queſtion were no other than two aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Potentates, that made unjuſt and cruel Wars upon their <hi>Neighbours,</hi> without provocation given, and therefore were moſt juſtly ſubdued by <hi>Bellerophon</hi> and <hi>Hercules,</hi> and they no leſs juſtly rewarded for the benefit received by their glorious <hi>Actions,</hi> which even exceed all Fame. Vertue is Vertue ſtill un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alterable; from whence we may conclude, that the ſame <hi>Glory</hi> ſtill attends, and that the ſame ſucceſs will prove the <hi>ſubduing</hi> theſe <hi>Chimaera</hi>'s and <hi>Hydra</hi>'s of Men, that for ſo long time have harraſ'd <hi>Europe</hi> with wicked <hi>Wars,</hi> and impious <hi>Depopu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations,</hi> merely to gain the Honour of being like thoſe Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, <hi>Terrors</hi> and <hi>Deſtroyers</hi> of <hi>Mankind.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="catalogue">
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:43542:38"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of <hi>French</hi> Commodities Yearly tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported into <hi>England,</hi> by which it appears that our Trade with <hi>France</hi> has been at leaſt Sixteen Hundred Thouſand Pounds a Year, clear loſs to this Kingdom.</head>
            <p n="1">1. THere is tranſported out of <hi>France</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> great quantities of Velvets plain and wrought, Sattins plain and wrought, Cloth of Gold and Silver, Armoyſins and other Merchandiſes of Silk, which are made at <hi>Lions,</hi> and are valued to be Yearly worth one Hundred and Fifty Thouſand Pounds.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In Silk, Stuffs, Taffeties, Poudeſoys, Armoyſins, Cloths of Gold and Silver, Tabbies plain and wrought, Silk-ribbands, and other ſuch like Silk ſtuffs as are made at <hi>Tours,</hi> valued to be worth above Three Hundred Thouſand Pounds a Year.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In Silk-ribbands, Gallowns, Laces, and Buttons of Silk, which are made at <hi>Paris, Roan, Chimont,</hi> St. <hi>Eſtienes</hi> in <hi>Forreſts,</hi> for about one Hundred and Fifty Thouſand Pounds a Year.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A great quantity of Serges, which are made at <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons, Chartres, Eſtamines</hi> and <hi>Rhemes,</hi> and great quantities of Serges made at <hi>Amiens, Crevecoeur, Blicourt,</hi> and other Towns in <hi>Picardy,</hi> for above one Hundred and Fifty Thouſand Pounds a Year.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In Bever, Demicaſtor and Felt Hats, made in the City and Suburbs of <hi>Paris;</hi> beſides many others made at <hi>Roan, Lions,</hi> and other places, for about One Hundred and Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Thouſand Pounds a Year.</p>
            <p n="6">6. In Feathers, Belts, Girdles, Hatbands, Fans, Hoods, Masks, gilt and wrought Looking-glaſſes, Cabinets Watches, Pictures, Caſes, Medals, Tablets, Bracelets, and other ſuch like Merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ware, for above One Hundred and Fifty Thouſand Pounds a Year.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:43542:39"/>7. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Pins, Needles, Box-combs, Tortoiſe-ſhell Combs, and ſuch like, for about Twenty Thouſand Pound a Year.</p>
            <p n="8">8. In perfumed and trimmed Gloves, that are made at <hi>Paris, Roan, Vendoſme, Clermont,</hi> and other places, for about Ten Thouſand Pounds a Year.</p>
            <p n="9">9. In Papers of all ſorts. which are made at <hi>Auvergne, Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctou, Limoſin, Champaigne</hi> and <hi>Normandy</hi> for above One Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Thouſand Pounds a Year.</p>
            <p n="10">10. In all ſorts of Iron-mongers wares that are made in <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, Auvergne,</hi> and other places, for about Fourty Thouſand Pounds a Year.</p>
            <p n="11">11. In Linen Cloth that is made in <hi>Bretaigne,</hi> and <hi>Normandy</hi> as well courſe as fine, there is tranſported into <hi>England,</hi> for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove Four Hundred Thouſand Pounds a Year.</p>
            <p n="12">12. In Houſhold-ſtuff, conſiſting of Beds Matreſſes, Cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lids, Hangings, Fringes of Silk, and other furniture, for above One Hundred thouſand Pounds a Year.</p>
            <p n="13">13. In Wines from <hi>Gaſcoigne, Nantois</hi> and other places on the River of <hi>Loyerc</hi> and alſo from <hi>Bourdeaux, Rochel, Nante, Roan,</hi> and other places, are tranſported into <hi>England</hi> for above Six Hundred Thouſand Pounds a Year.</p>
            <p n="14">14. In <hi>Aqua Vitae,</hi> Sider, Vineger, Verjuice, and ſuch like, for about One Hundred Thouſand Pounds a Year.</p>
            <p n="15">15. In Saffron, Caſtle-ſope, Honey, Almonds, Olives Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, Prunes, and ſuch like, for about One Hundred and Fifty Thouſand Pounds a Year.</p>
            <p n="16">16. Beſides five or ſix hundred Veſſels of Salt laden at <hi>Ma ron, Rochel, Rouage,</hi> the Iſle of <hi>Oleron,</hi> and Iſle of <hi>Rhee,</hi> tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported into <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> of a very great value. So as by this calculation, it doth appear, that the yearly value of ſuch commodities as are tranſported from <hi>France</hi> to <hi>England,</hi> amount to above Six and Twenty Hundred Thouſand Pounds.</p>
            <p>And the commodities exported out of <hi>England</hi> into <hi>France,</hi> conſiſting chiefly of Woollen Cloths, Serges, Knit Stockings, Lead, Pewter, Alume, Coals, and all elſe, do not amount to above Ten Hundred Thouſand Pounds a Year. By which it appears that our Trade with <hi>France</hi> is at leaſt ſixteen Hundred Thouſand Pounds a Year, clear loſt to this Kingdom.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:43542:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
